Hi, welcome to the Physionic Podcast,
which is now, you could say, has become
the annual Physionic Podcast because the
last episode was about a year ago. So, I
planned on doing these every 3 months or
so, but as you can see, that didn't end
up panning out. Um, and I'm not putting
myself under too much pressure on this
podcast simply because, uh, I've got
other aspects of physionic that I have
to focus on. But that said, I do have a
number of topics I'd like to discuss
with you today. And for those of you
that put on the podcast to fall asleep,
then rejoice. You have more material to
fall asleep to. Uh speaking to that, I'm
going to, assuming that YouTube allows
me, I'm going to turn off the ads like I
usually do uh throughout the podcast. So
hopefully you won't be interrupted with
any sort of, you know, annoying uh
advertisements throughout. But if not,
then I apologize. I would YouTube makes
a lot of different changes to to ad
policy uh over time. So, we'll see.
Anyway, at any rate, uh if you'd like to
listen to the podcast, so aside from
just watching it, just to be clear,
there's not nothing going to be on
screen. This is a purely perfectly raw
video of me just talking to the camera.
I'm probably just going to be relaxing
on my couch on this extremely gloomy
Sunday that I have uh behind me. So, I
thought it would just be the perfect
opportunity to discuss some science, get
into some of your commentary. I got some
really good comments uh some good push
back as well as some questions that
people brought up on the topics that
we're going to be covering. And speaking
to that, uh, last time I think I covered
every single topic that I had covered
before, uh, or after the last podcast. I
can't do that this time because I think
I've released what, maybe 70 or 80
different investigations, different
videos, different analyses, uh, since
the last podcast. So, uh, it is, well,
actually probably more than that.
Probably closer to well over a hundred.
So, there's no way I'm going to be
sitting here. Although the previous
podcasts were, you know, three hours,
five hours long, there's no way that I'm
going to be sitting here and talking for
like three days. So, I've picked out
specific topics I think are especially
uh useful or interesting and things that
I wanted to discuss and I think that uh
you'll hopefully find interesting as
well. Uh if you're one of those people
that believes that a person should just
get to the point, um I've probably
already dragged on too long on that
front. So uh first of all, I think those
individuals don't understand what a
podcast means. But the second thing I
can say is that I will supply links uh
under the video so that you can click on
the link and then go to a much shortened
version of uh what I'm going to be
discussing. But you will miss out on
some of the commentary that I'm going to
be covering. Uh because one of the
benefits is that with the comments that
I can retrospectively go back and kind
of highlight the top comments that
people have liked a lot so they rise to
the top and then I can uh discuss those
uh under each topic. Okay. Well, with
that uh I don't know if I mentioned it
already because I had to redo this
introduction two times already. Uh there
is a link to the podcast. It's
completely free. Um, you can just click
on the link and, you know, sign up
through Spotify or Apple Podcast or
whatever you like to use. Um, just be
sure to know that it's not a weekly
podcast. It's not a monthly podcast.
It's not even at this point a quarterly
podcast. It's just really whenever I
feel or have the the chance to sit down
and do these extended uh stays. But that
said, let's get into it a little bit.
I've got my notes here. So, we're going
to dive into I'd say maybe seven or so
topics, maybe maybe a bit more. Um, and
also go over your commentary. All right.
So, the first topic
is collagen on skin. So, this is a topic
that I've covered a number of times at
this point. The
when I initially covered it, I had come
to the conclusion that the collagen
studies that had released on skin had
indicated a benefit of consuming
collagen peptides on reversing skin
wrinkling uh improving skin hydration,
improving skin elasticity, things of
that nature. That was maybe a year ago
and I think I covered that in one of the
previous podcast episodes. However, then
there was this new analysis that
released uh this year in 2025, maybe a
few months ago, wherein the researchers
in their overall conclusion said uh yes,
collagen peptides seem to be effective
for improving uh skin and all the the
different metrics that I had mentioned.
However, uh what they also did, what was
unique about that analysis, that meta
analysis, and I think they went over
maybe 20 or so studies, 28 studies, 24
studies, something along those lines.
All of them were randomized control
trials. And what they did is they
divided the studies based off of funding
source as well as the quality of
evidence. as in um for metaanalyses what
they'll do is they'll go through a
Cochran risk of bias assessment or a ROB
scale or they'll go through a grade
scale and they're very similar to one
another and there's different versions
of these different scales but it's
essentially a standardized system by
which the researchers go through
question by question
of you know is it are is the study
double blind? Is the study uh
randomized? Is the study, you know,
there's there's a bunch of different
questions that they have to answer for
every single study that they include
into the analysis. And then they give
each study a score. I think it's a
three-point score. So, it they us either
get a red ticker, a yellow ticker, or a
green ticker. Green meaning low risk of
bias, red meaning high risk of bias. And
if you're thinking yellow is moderate
risk of bias, you might be able to call
it that, but it's really more so unknown
risk of bias. And like I said, there's
different iterations of this. So they
ended up breaking up the studies based
off of the funding source if it was
industry funded. So funded by let's say
a collagen company or a skin company and
by the quality. So was it low risk of
bias in all these different questions.
And what they ended up showing after you
got over the overall conclusion is that
this analysis indicated that when you
broke things up by those standards that
the
studies that were industry funded
indicated that there was benefit of
collagen peptides on skin and the
studies that were not industry funded or
industry affiliated. So they had
independent funding maybe by like a
university or some sort of internal
funding for that institution
that they
would show no benefit or largely no
benefit of collagen peptides on skin. So
on the surface of it, you'd think, okay,
well then that's pretty clear. It's, you
know, I've always been on this side of
I'm not going to dismiss a a study
simply because it's industry funded,
but now that we actually have evidence
at this point of, okay, well, the
non-industry funded studies indicate
that there's no benefit, I'm going to
side with those studies over the
industry funded studies. if you actually
have that comparison. However, when you
open up the analysis
and go further into the details of that
analysis, you look so for a lot of these
meta analyses, they'll list all the
studies and then they'll tell you, you
know, it's basically a big table of with
the studies on the left side and then a
bunch of different, you know,
information like the study length, the
participants, the participants age, the
participants weight, uh all these
different factors, you know, get put
into a table so it's just easy to read
so you don't have to open up each each
individual study and at the very end of
this table they had put the funding
source and then they had also put the
outcome so what happened when collagen
peptides were compared against placebo
and I ended up looking at every all of
the
non-industry funded studies so the ones
that they had said that if you pull all
that data together that you don't see a
benefit of collagen peptides. And six
out of seven of the studies, there were
seven studies total, six out of seven of
those studies
indicated
a benefit of collagen peptides on skin.
Only one study showed no effect.
So, that's probably pretty confusing to
you because you you're thinking, well,
hold on. You just said that the
non-industry funded studies showed no
effect and the industry funded studies
showed an effect and now I'm saying the
opposite. So what's with the
pingponging? Well, the answer is because
the researchers and what researchers do
is that they speak in very scientific
terms as in they use this type of
language that is uh if you're not in the
field, it's difficult to interpret and
it's it can be it can be misleading.
We'll just put it that way. Simply
because they say there was no result.
I'm paraphrasing obviously. uh there was
no result, but what they actually meant
was that there's no statistically
significant result. But then when you
actually look at the data, looked at the
grouped data,
you notice that oh well, the reason why
there's no statistically significant
result is because they don't have enough
power in the analysis to detect an
effect, which means that they don't have
enough data included in the analysis to
detect an effect. And so to break that
down further, what I mean by that is if
we had 28 studies total, fund, industry
funded and non-industry funded, we have
28 studies. That's a lot of data.
But then once you you create this
subgroup analysis where you break it up
by funding, meaning we've got this group
of industry funded studies. So if that's
28 minus 7, that would be 21. Hopefully
I did my math right. So that's 21
studies for the industry funded and they
do show an effect. Then you have seven
studies for the non-industry funded and
they don't show an effect. Now the
question is well is it because there's
truly no effect or is it because you
don't have enough data to detect an
effect? And it turns out that the answer
is probably the latter. And the reason
for that is because if you look at each
one of those studies, six out of seven
do show an effect of collagen peptides
on skin. So if you were to look at the
individual studies, you'd be like, "Oh
yeah, for sure collagen peptides are
effective uh for for skin."
But when you group that data together
and then you apply meta metaanalytical
statistical analyses to it. So you know
doing a bunch of mathematics to it then
you have to consider
the certainty of the evidence. And
because you've shrunk the pool of data
from 28 studies to seven studies the
certainty of the data becomes a lot less
certain. So that ultimately yields
a situation where you have to report it
in scientific speak as no statistically
significant effect of collagen peptides
on skin. And that's kind of that's kind
of where we landed. So
you can run with that and say, "Oh,
okay. Well, then there's no effect of
collagen peptides in the real world on
skin. Or you can say, oh, we just need
more data to be input into this to
really detect an effect. And if we were
to just look at the individual studies,
we would we would actually see an effect
because you'd be six versus one
indicating effectiveness.
So some people
didn't do that part of the study
analysis
and therefore in my opinion came to the
wrong conclusion. Uh but I could easily
see you know an argument for a person
wanting to be exactly by the letter of
the law the statistical significance did
not indicate you know any effect. I will
say for a lot of these subgroup analyses
they do kind of like sub subgroup
analyses where they look at the
non-industry funded studies and then
they cross examine those with the
quality of the evidence. to remember the
ROB scale that I was talking about, the
grade scale that I was talking about.
And then you're taking the seven studies
that you have, which is already a small
pool of studies for in this situation,
and you're cutting it down to even fewer
studies. So now you're looking at like
two studies or one study and trying to
make a metaanalytical
uh conclusion based off of that, you
know, one study or two studies. and then
you're shrinking the amount of data that
you have even further. So, you know, you
could make an argument either way. If
you're a purist and you just want to go
by statistical significance, then you
would say yes, there's I guess I'll say
no, there's no effect of of collagen
peptides on skin.
If you are a person who's a little more
flexible when looking at data, which I
tend to be, I think I'm kind of in the
middle between between like, oh, that's
a joke to just look at statistical
significance and the more strict people
that are saying only look at statistical
significance. I'm kind of in the middle
there. But if you are more flexible in
that way, then you would say, oh, okay,
well, there's probably an effect here.
We just don't have the data. we don't
have enough data to really detect that
effect and I will say for some of the
subgroup analyses it got very close even
though there was very little data uh you
know again relatively speaking so then
there were two critiques that I
addressed as well one
was that
collagen peptides are never
compared against protein
and I think that's a that's an excellent
critique That's true. That in none of
the studies that I've looked at, I don't
think any of the studies that were
included in this analysis do they
compare against protein.
And that's problematic because it's
possible that it's not the collagen
peptides themselves, but it's once
they're hydrayed. So you you consume
collagen peptides meaning that they're
in these two and three amino acids that
are stitched together as in they're
molecular molecularly bound to one
another. So they're still together as
opposed to single amino acids which is
what you think of like for glycine or
methionine or leucine or whatnot. But in
this situation they're still stitched
together as these die or tripeptides.
And the argument for the protein
perspective is that well if you just
consume enough protein of those amino
acids that make up collagen then you
will no longer see an effect of uh
collagen peptides a unique we'll call it
a unique effect of collagen peptides and
that's a that's a perfectly fair
argument to make and
I don't have a great rebuttal against
that simply because we don't have that
evidence except for I think one burn
study. So people that were burned
had like secondderee or third degree
burns or something along those lines and
they were they were randomized to be
given
collagen peptides or they were
randomized to be given protein and the
collagen peptides did see an improvement
in their skin recovery over the protein
condition. But that was a single study
and I think I don't remember off the top
of my head but there there were a few
things that you know kind of like what
we're talking about like I wish they had
done this kind of situation. So I I I
don't want to base the entire push back
against the protein argument simply
based off of this single study. I think
that there's a lot more that uh that we
need to see. So I think that's up in the
air. It's certainly a possibility. I
will say that mechanistically there has
been evidence where the collagen
peptides themselves have had an effect
on uh cells and
I even covered a study which I recently
discovered on collagen peptides versus a
protein in an in vitro. on cells and I
covered this a little bit for the
insider version of my my analysis on uh
what we're talking about here is skin
but ultimately they showed that there
was a unique effect of collagen peptides
over protein. So you know this
smidge of evidence that pushes back
against this protein idea but I just
don't think that it's strong enough yet
to really dismiss that idea. So from a
skin perspective, yes, I think that we
need comparisons to to really tease out
if there's a unique effect. That's
really what the question we're trying to
get to or trying to answer. Is there a
unique effect of collagen peptides? is
if I can do the same with just consuming
more protein or a particular type of
amino acid or whatever, I'd probably
prefer to do that than to go with the
collagen themselves simply because
collagen is probably going to be an
added expense on top of, you know,
protein, which is much more readily
available.
The other push back that I sort of
thought about in my own head that I
don't really hear all that often, but I
still think of it as a decent push back
is, well, shouldn't seven studies be
enough to detect an effect? And I think
I've got a twofold answer to that. One
is that even though six out of seven
studies show an effect, I don't think
I've ever claimed that collagen peptides
are going to turn you, I think in my
video I said from Alpuccino now to
Aluccino back in like Scarface or The
Godfather. It's not going to, you know,
dial back time by 50 years or anything
like that. um what it's going to do is
lead to some mild improvements in skin
elasticity, hydration, and uh wrinkling
and whatnot and maybe has a protective
effect over time as well in in
mitigating some of that uh as as the
aging process occurs. So, it's a mild
effect. I've always said that it's a
mild effect
but you know for some people having that
mild effect is uh is important. So you
know
the other aspect other than just looking
at the effect size is the overall time
horizon for a lot of these studies. So,
we're looking at, you know, 12 weeks, 8
weeks, maybe 16 weeks, which isn't no
time, but, you know, when you're
thinking about reversing some signs of
aging and whatnot, it's possible that we
might see greater effects. And if all
the studies, if all six studies that
showed an effect in the non-industry
funded studies, if all six of those
studies had lasted for like 3 years or a
year or something along those lines,
maybe the effect size would be large
enough that we would be able to tease
out some of those differences. Um, I I
realize I'm getting a bit technical
here. I'm kind of giving myself some
leeway for this podcast. Um
maybe I'm banking on the people that are
going to fall asleep to this.
Um helping them out by uh by
getting into some of those
technicalities. But the point here, the
main point here to take away
is that collagen peptides
seem to be based on this analysis as
well as others seem to be effective for
improving your skin. It's a mild effect.
Don't expect anything completely
transformative or anything, but it will
have a mild effect on your skin. And
that seems to be consistent definitely
in industry funded studies, but there is
even a signal in non-industry funded
studies. I think that's that's where I
would leave that. Okay.
Actually, that's not where I'm going to
leave things because I've got two more
uh things to discuss.
I've repeated this many times, but
people will bring up, well, what about
the mechanism? How does that make any
sense? Why why can't I just eat more
protein? Which, by the way, on the
protein front, one more thing I will
quick add is that it doesn't make a
whole lot of sense to me to to try to
equate the protein to collagen. So, here
we are. I was thinking I was going to
just give you takeaways and those
takeaways are accurate, but I'm going to
be talking about this for a little bit
longer because I just had another few
ideas. So, if in a in a study, you would
typically want to equate the amount of
protein to the amount of collagen that
you consume. So if you're consuming an
additional let's say 15 g of hydrayzeed
collagen and then you would want in the
the control condition to be consuming 15
additional grams of a protein, right? To
compare because if you're consuming a
100 more grams of protein, well that's
kind of unfair. Um so to to actually
tease out that unique effect and
in that situation it seems unlikely to
me. I mean, maybe you disagree, but it
seems unlikely to me that 10 or 15 more
grams of protein is suddenly going to
have these lead to these positive skin
effects. 10 to 15 grams of protein in
the grand scheme of things isn't a whole
lot. So, I find it unlikely that we
would see any sort of
similarity between the collagen and the
protein. But the the main critique that
people will say is that it's it's the
components of the collagen. So like the
glycine and the proline and whatnot that
that are leading to these collagen
producing cells, fibiberblasts,
uh condraittes,
but in this situation, we're talking
about fiberblasts
that these cells take up these amino
acids and then they use them to produce
more collagen. So, we might as well just
consume more proteins that have these
amino acids and then they'll also still
be given the requisite amino acids to
then produce collagen. And that's that's
fine, but that's not actually the
argument for collagen. The collagen
peptides
that get absorbed, and they do get
absorbed, that's another question I get
asked. And we have human evidence
indicating that people who consume
collagen peptides or not necessarily
collagen peptides but peptides of dual
amino acids and triple amino acids still
bound together. They do end up in the
bloodstream. So that for sure we know
it's not just single amino acids that
get into the bloodstream. Then the
second thing is well then once they're
in the bloodstream are they just taken
up by the cells to be then produced into
collagen? And the argument by a lot of
like cell biologists and people that
know physiology will say well those
cells will then probably take up even if
they did take up the deptides and the
tripeptides
they would then break them up. So they
would still end up as single amino acids
within the cells. And that's there's
some truth to that. I mean, I'm not
disagreeing, but the real argument is
that it's not actually what happens
inside the cell. It's actually what
happens on the surface of the cell.
Because we've discovered that there are
multiple collagen peptide receptors on
the surface of the cell. And if that's
the case, then the collagen peptides
actually interact with the cell surface
to the cell uh collagen receptor. And
then that leads to a change in the
signaling within the cell. So it's not
the actual components of the collagen
peptide that lead to more collagen
peptide production because now you have
more of the building blocks. But it's
the actual binding which convinces the
cell to produce more mature collagen
fibers which get deposited into the skin
layer. That's kind of the idea. Now, I
will admit that I don't think that we
have foolproof evidence that this is
exactly how it works. Mainly because the
reviews that I know of and when I opened
up a lot of the studies, what they show
is that these receptors bind to already
present collagen fibers. Is it possible
that the collagen peptides could
interact with these receptors and cause
similar benefits? Yeah, it is. But my
whole overall point is that there's a
lot of unknowns that we're still trying
to tease out, but so far the evidence
still seems to be leaning towards uh
collagen peptides having a unique
effect. And that may, you know, one day
shift completely to the other side. So
for those people that are like, well
doc, you know, people say one thing one
day, then they say something else for
another day. It's because everything I'm
explaining here, this thought process of
like, here's where the evidence, what we
know, here's what we're kind of
speculating, but there's a few little
gaps here that we need to figure out.
Here's what we don't know anything
about.
This is the kind of thought process that
scientists have to go through just to
give an intellectually honest answer. So
once we start plugging in more of that
information, we once we start
discovering some more of that
information, it could very much shift to
a more complete answer that ultimately
leads to an opposite conclusion. And
that's why the field grows, right?
Science grows. That's why the the whole
idea of things developing over time. Um
it's just unfortunately social media is
not just does not lead to a
environment where people can can explain
a lot of those nuances. It's just
everybody wants the information
basically injected into their brain or
transmitted. If you speak for just a
second too long then you know you
immediately get hit with complaints of
well this was too long. you just get to
the point, all that stuff. So, you know,
you get caught between these two areas
of like this is the level of
explanation. So, if I were to be talking
with you, you know, one-on-one, this is
how I'd be explaining it to you. I'd be
asking I'd first open the conversation
by saying, uh, how much time do you
have? Uh, and if it's an elevator pitch,
I'll be like, there's a lot of holes in
the research that we still need to
figure out, but so far the evidence
leans to collagen peptides being a
benefit for your skin. Have a great day.
But then if a person's like, I want to
know everything there is to know about
the certainty of the evidence and just
like explain the mechanisms and explain
the physiology, explain the data, like
where the clinical trials, what the
clinical trials show. talk to me about
the funding sources. We would be here
for however long it's been. I don't know
the time because my camera is all the
way over there. Uh but yeah, it's been
about half an hour. I'm seeing by my
recorder here. So, it would be that
level of discussion
for me to explain where we are. All
right. Who's going to sit here except
for you, poor soul, uh, listening to me
ramble on on my couch about collagen?
Very few people. So,
you're just a special person. So, yeah,
the that's why I'm saying social media
is going to seem like it's
flip-flopping. And another aspect is
there are some people that are just
grifting, bottom line. Okay, so that all
said, I wanted to cover some comments
like I did last few podcasts. I do enjoy
this. Hopefully people feel like they're
they're uh being heard. Again, I'm
picking the among the top comments under
some of these videos. So, Burnham's
ghost,
that's the name of the commenter,
said, "As a case study, I can say this.
I've had five knee surgeries, two ACL
reconstructions,
just as a side note. Wow, that's that's
a lot. Uh speedy recovery. That's that's
a lot. Uh maybe a a player of some sort.
I don't know. Maybe a
uh getting up there in age. Maybe a
combination of the two. Anyway,
continuing. Increasing knee pain over
the decades, especially after military
service. Okay. Well, there's your
explanation. Over this decade, over the
decades, I tried everything and nothing
really allowed or showed promise until I
started taking collagen. I was able to
start running again. And when pain does
emerge, it subsides much more quickly
than before. I think I'm less likely to
be a victim of the placebo effect in
this case because I've tried so many
things and started out as very
skeptical.
Yeah. So this is obviously anecdote but
um and this was highly uh you know
bumped up by by people uh but that's
that's certainly a possibility like I
said you know and I'll say this and I've
said this in the past that the
scientific literature can sometimes be
pretty far behind
the anecdotes that come out. So people
will try something and they'll
experience significant benefit from
that, but then when you look in the
scientific literature, there's almost no
data or no good data on that topic. So
does that mean that that thing doesn't
work? No, it doesn't. But that said,
you're also kind of caught between a
rock and a hard place because you also
can't say that all anecdotes are
accurate, right? And as a matter of
fact, I would probably say the majority
aren't
simply because you know exactly what
Burnham Burnham's ghost said that
there's a placebo effect, but then
there's also like many other things that
a person might change at the same time.
Um, so there's there's it's more
correlational than it is causitive. Um,
there's a lot of different factors. So,
kind of hard to tease out, but based on
this person's experience
and they're talking primarily for joint
health and improving um you know, from
from surgery recovery and whatnot. Um,
and I do have topics I I have looked at
collagen on joint health, which actually
wasn't quite as strong as it was for uh
skin. But even so, this person is saying
things that align their anecdote aligns
with uh what some of the research
indicates. I think that the the benefits
they're experiencing are probably far
more than mild benefits, though. Okay.
Astrolab had said, uh, one thing I
noticed on these studies is that they
span a short time. Okay. uh for example
your joints, you notice that the
benefits aren't great. But for someone
suffering with osteoarthritis, which is
degenerative and with no cure, it's an
awesome result to have less pain after a
year rather than more pain. Same with
wrinkles. Maybe the effects compound
over time and after 3 years you are one
year younger rather than 3 years older,
which is still great. And that's that's
absolutely true. So if we had studies
that lasted for longer periods of time,
we'd be able to that effect slowly grows
over time or at least it could. It has
the potential to grow over time and we
just we can try to project that
outwards. We can try to estimate that
outwards, but that doesn't actually mean
that we've collected the data to show
that that's actually the case. And yeah,
so that's true. And the thing is though,
you're probably not going to get studies
that are going to last three years
unlike collagen and skin or collagen and
even your joints
simply because
it's very expensive and they're going to
use really sensitive metrics to try to
tease out if there's an effect. And once
they find an effect, they're going to
cut the the the study's going to end.
Um, and when they don't need
a whole year or multiple years to detect
an effect, why run a study and spend
hundreds of thousands more dollars just
to end up at the same conclusion?
Although admittedly on then social
media, people will say, well, you know,
they've got this critique and this
critique and whatnot. And some of the
those critiques are absolutely fair.
It's just that researchers can't go to
the NIH or they can't go to their
funding agency and be like, "Hey, uh, so
we could detect an effect in 12 weeks,
but it's going to be a really small
effect. So we'd really love to find a
really big effect because uh, we want to
know what happens over many years. So
would you mind like floating us a couple
million dollars more uh just so we can
say that there's a bigger effect than
there was
usually that's not that's not going to
fly. Uh that's not enough of a reason to
spend millions of dollars. So uh yeah
time is a huge factor when it comes to
studies especially randomized control
trials but uh we're unfortunately not
going to get those uh those data. Okay.
I think I've sufficiently rambled on
enough about collagen and skin. Let's
get into another interesting topic to
me. One that actually wasn't that
popular, but I wanted to cover it anyway
because, well, I'm just going to allow
myself to be a bit selfish here. That's
ketones
having a relationship with worse liver
health. And the way I framed this
initially was to point out that yes,
there was a study that showed a
relationship between higher blood ketone
levels and worse liver health. So that's
a relationship, that's an association,
that's a correlation.
But
what it doesn't tell us is if the
ketones are causing this
poor liver health or if it's the poor
liver health that the ketones are
actually trying to help with or if
something else is going on here. It just
shows us a simple association of ketones
and liver health. However,
when what the researchers ended up doing
was they generated mice that had a
inability to produce ketones and then
they measured their liver health when
they taxed these mice to have worse
liver health. And what they showed is
that the mice that were still able to
produce ketones had dramatically
diminished
liver fattiness and liver damage and
liver fibrosis and just overall worse
liver health.
While the mice that had ketone
production blocked, known as
ketogenesis,
they had far worse liver health, as in
they had more fatty deposits in the
liver, more fibrosis, etc., etc. So, the
takeaway from this was that
the excess ketone production is not a
negative. It's actually quite the
opposite. It's almost like a re release
valve for the liver because if you're
not aware, the liver is where uh ketones
are produced. So the liver is producing
ketones to essentially try to tamp down
any sort of fat accumulation inside of
the liver. So think of like fatty liver
disease. So the ketones are a way to
take the fat droplets or the fat
molecules that would be stored in fat
droplets within the liver cells, the
hpatocytes,
and have them flux through the
mitochondrian
and the powerhouse of the cell. And that
mitochondrian will then convert those
fatty acids to ketones and then eject
them back out of the cell. So, and the
the m the the liver cell has a number of
different ways that it can try to deal
with these fat molecules that would
otherwise accumulate in the liver cell.
So, it can package them into LDL
particles and then eject them out of the
liver. It can metabolize them so it can
use them for energy, but there it can
only do that up to a certain amount
because the cell only needs a certain
amount of energy. and a certain point
it's just not going to need anymore
or
because the liver has this ability it
can produce ketones.
So once you knock one of those systems
out, the ketone production, then it has
to rely on the two other systems that it
has and and this is speculation on my
part and that's what ultimately leads to
a lot of stress that could occur in the
liver if you don't have a ketogenesis
available.
So ketogenesis in that scenario
indicates a protective effect of the
liver. Okay. So then I took it a step
further because this was all in animal
models trying to figure out mechanisms
of how ketones are protective and all
that good stuff. And that's great.
However, then I was interested in
obviously the human research. And the
human research pretty dramatically shows
that low carb diets, fasting, whatever,
however you want to improve increase
your ketone levels because a very low
carbohydrate diet like a ketogenic diet
and fasting are two of the most potent
ways of increasing your ketone
production. And both of them lead to
significant improvements in liver
health. So,
and there's probably some nuances there
that I need to get into in more depth,
but you know, overall
both of those were great ways of
reducing
fat that's surrounded and inside of uh
the liver. So, I thought that was just
such a cool study to to try to figure
out how ketone production and that's a
key point there is it's not the ketones
themselves, although maybe ketones have
additional benefits, but the study was
really trying to tease out what does the
production of ketones, so the actual
metabolic
flux that has to occur for those ketones
to be produced, how does that impact
liver health? And that seems to be a
positive. So that association that we
were talking about earlier or that I was
rambling about earlier is that the the
most likely
as liver health is getting worse, the
ketone production is increasing because
it's trying to again eliminate as much
of that fatty liver uh disease as as
possible. However,
that
doesn't necessarily mean that it can it
can actually deal with that poor liver
health. So, um you know, ultimately
they're both going to track together as
in ketone levels get higher and higher
as liver health uh gets worse and worse.
But
it, you know, it's like the body
constantly trying to compensate and it
just can't keep up with the the
worsening of the the liver health. Also,
I just want to be clear, just because
you have high ketones doesn't mean that
you have bad liver health. Um, because
again, it's just an association. One may
be causing the other. Uh, but it's not
the ketones that are causing the the
poor liver health or at least based not
based on this research. So anyway, just
uh a fascinating study I thought I'd
share. Now a few uh comments.
Robert Stanton said, "In 2019, I was
diagnosed with non-alcoholic fatty liver
disease with NASH, which is
non-alcoholic steattosis
steic
hepatit. Nope,
I'm going to struggle with that one."
But it's another uh type of liver
disease. Um steattoic
is yeah, I think that's one of that's
the S in there, but I can't remember the
H. It's just fallen right out of my
head. And F3 F4 fibrosis. By changing to
a ketogenic diet, I completely reverse
my liver uh disease. And according to
the latest fibrokin report, my liver is
now normal. That's all I need to know.
That's what Robert said. So, first off,
Robert, I don't you're probably not
listening to this, but um first of all,
that's amazing. That's genuinely
incredible. I mean, it's incredible at
any point to have such advanced levels
of uh liver disease or any sort of
disease and then to be able to change
your routine or change your nutrition or
something along those lines and then to
see such significant benefits uh that
fight against this uh this disease
state. So, and that takes a lot of
willpower and it takes a lot of uh I'm
going to change something about myself
and that in its own right just on a
human level without any of this
scientific uh garbage
is an incredible feat. So, huge congrats
to you. Um the only other thing I'll
say, well actually two things. One is
obviously that's again very much in line
with what the research indicates. The
other thing that I will say is that
I
I get this um I get a lot of these
comments from people that say and that's
all I need to know.
And on one hand I completely well I
shouldn't say completely on one hand I
agree but on the other hand there's a
tug inside of me that's like
unfortunately I think that that
mentality ends up
pushing
into other areas of
scientific communication or nutrition
and whatnot and we end up
I don't know how phrase this exactly.
We end up discounting
scientific evidence simply because
something has happened a certain way to
us. So
I'll give you an example using this
exact situation. So if I use a low carb
diet and or let's say I use fasting
and I reverse my fatty liver disease
and then
I say something along the lines of well
that's all I need to know. I know
fasting is the end all beall for me. It
it almost it's not always the case, but
oftentimes people will then get so
focused on this one thing and they say,
"Well, this is the thing that worked for
me, so therefore it is the thing that
will work for everyone." And that's not
necessarily the case because a person
could try like a Mediterranean diet for
example, so something completely
different and get the same results.
And
those both can be true. So you can have
one thing that is really impactful and
really helped you as as an individual,
but that doesn't mean that other things
can't help. And I'm not isolating Robert
here, just to be clear. Uh but just the
the overall thought process just because
I see these kinds of comments all the
time, especially if people will use it
as a reputation of the evidence at hand.
So if you know if there's a study that
says you know low carb diet is better
than a Mediterranean diet for let's
again let's stick with the theme of
reversing liver disease and then a
person who's been using a Mediterranean
diet well is like well
I used a Mediterranean diet and it
worked really well for me. It works I
tried a low carb diet. did not work for
me, but a Mediterranean diet that did
work for me. And that's all I need to
know. Like, that's fine. I No, nobody's
disagreeing with you on that. But it's
not a reputation of the science. It it's
like there many things that can be true.
And
it's it's it's really difficult to
communicate that stuff again in in short
videos, like punchy videos that are that
are trying to get to the the overall
point with within a reasonable amount of
time. Very much again, I'll just crap on
this podcast again, unlike what I'm
doing uh right now, which I'm sure I'll
get comments on.
Anyway, the big point here though,
Robert is really fantastic. I'm really
happy for you genuinely and uh keep it
up. I hope that it stays that way. Um I
can't imagine that it wouldn't, but uh
yeah, keep it up. The next one is from
James uh Sales
Sales Sas.
I I'll move on. uh in my N of one
research. So anecdote again, I resolved
my non-alcoholic fatty liver disease
with ketogenic
and carnivoreish
diet and lost 48 pounds in 6 months.
This is confirmed by MRI imaging and as
GDT uh lab results. Thanks for the
video. So first off, thanks James.
Secondly, again, just like with Robert,
huge congratulations. That's no easy
feat. Um, especially losing 48 pounds as
well over 6 months. That's really
fantastic work. Um, James is talking
about for ALT and GGGT, those are
enzymes that are secreted out of the
liver when it is uh being harmed. So
when there's harm occurring to the liver
and
so if you see a reduction in them that
means that the the liver is in a better
uh situation and also confirmed by MRI
imaging as mentioned. So again, that's
that's fantastic. And
again, if if we to look at the
scientific literature,
you know, if you drop 48 pounds or if
you just drop weight in general, you
will typically see improvements in your
liver markers, you will see improvements
in your liver. So, it's not like a
person has to prescribe themselves to a
very specific diet because that's the
just because we're discussing right now
we're talking about low carb diets.
We're talking about fasting and whatnot
and how those are beneficial for liver
health. That doesn't mean that there
aren't better ways or different ways or
maybe not quite as effective ways but
still sustain like they're they're
better for you as an individual to use.
There's there's a lot of different ways
to attack something like that. And
especially when you are pairing that
with weight loss, it's a little bit
different maybe when a person is not
trying to lose weight. They're trying to
maintain their weight or even gain
weight but still maintain proper liver
health or improve their liver health.
But if you're losing weight, you that
that almost necessitates improvements in
your liver health. So just uh just
something that I would add. um you know,
if if a ketogenic or carnivore style
nutrition works for you, that's that's
great. There obviously, you know,
certain
other considerations that people have to
have to consider. Um, I'm not going to
go down that rabbit hole for the time
being, but the point being and the
overall point of my video and my
analysis and whatnot is that low carb
diets and fasting can certainly be an
improvement and a significant
improvement for uh, liver health. So,
for both really great and I'm genuinely
happy for you. All right, the next topic
is to cover drowning cancer in a fatty
molecule butyrate in this situation.
So, I covered this fascinating study,
uh, probably one of the most fascinating
of the year up to now, which essentially
looked at the impact that a fat, a short
chain fat called butyrate, has on
cancer, specifically colon cancer. And
what they showed is that butyrate can
not only inhibit the growth of colon
cancer but can kill colon cancer as
well. And I won't go into all the
details um but there's you know mass
cell death to the colon cancer that
while sparing healthy colon cells. So
colon being uh your large intestine. And
so if we were to to look at a person's
colon, probably not the most desirable
thing, but we're going to do it anyway.
Uh so you have your intestinal tract,
maybe if you if you had an image of uh
the intestines. If you were to zoom into
the intestines, and then you'd notice
that there are these these crypts, these
kind of uh grooves that create this like
snake like uh look almost. They they
look like caverns
that go into the intestinal wall and
then come back out and they actually
make up the intestinal wall. And inside
those grooves at the very bottom of that
groove, you have a bunch of stem cells.
And these stem cells end up multiplying
and uh turning into a variety of
different intestinal cells. If that's
panith cells or goblet cells or
colonocytes of other, you know, general
colonocytes,
there's a number of different cells that
they can turn into, but they ultimately
give the intestine structure, right? And
the intestine has a number of different
functions that again we don't really
need to get into. But it's at that exact
site. So at the very bottom of that
crypt that these stem cells if they
undergo mutation burden or if uh you
believe more of a metabolic environment
that ultimately leads to more of a
cancerous type of cell that starts
getting born and then that stem cell
that is now more cancerous starts to
multiply. So you start to get a tumor or
you start to get growth in in that
region that is abnormal growth and
that's obviously why we get
colonoscopies because we start to detect
some of those uh abnormal growths that
start to occur and we try to catch those
uh early. Okay. So why are we talking
about that in relation to butyrate?
Well, the reason is because as we
consume foods that ultimately get
produced into butyrate, that butyrate
can get into those crypts
and can be taken up by the cells.
And when they're taken up by the cells,
according to this research, the cells
end up uh kind of freezing like they
can't grow anymore. And in the worst
scenarios, they end up dying. And the
reason for that is because the cancer
cells, at least the specific ones that
were tested, the cancer cells are
using
sugar or carbohydrate as energy and they
are less able or less willing. less
able, less willing, kind of use those
interchangeably
um because we're getting to the limit of
my knowledge on the topic uh at this
point
to use fat molecules. So, because
they're using sugar, they're using
carbohydrates. And I I just want to be
clear here, I'm not using the word sugar
as in like Pepsi or whatever, although
that is also included in this
definition. And I'm talking about sugar
as carbohydrates, glucose specifically.
And carbohydrates are made of largely
glucose.
So when glucose enters inside this
cancer cell, it gets metabolized into
cellular energy as well as many other
things that again we don't need to get
into. But butyrate because it's a fat
can enter into the cancer cell. And
because the cancer cell is not going to
take that butyrate and produce it into
energy, it starts to accumulate inside
of the cancer cell. And because this
butyrate is just has no destination,
it's just being taken up into the cancer
cell because the cancer cell would
normally if it were a normal cell would
be taking up butyrate for energy
production.
This concentration of butyrate outside
the cell allows butyrate into the cell
and it starts to build up inside the
cancer cell. Now from there butyrate has
a number of different mechanisms that it
affects the cancer cell. So, one of the
main ones that was detailed was the fact
that it probably, we don't know if it's
direct or indirect, but it probably has
some sort of interaction with key
enzymes called HDAX or histone
deacetylases
and as well as
uh histone acetal transferases.
And what these two types of enzymes,
these families of enzymes do is they add
or remove a particular type of tag to
the DNA structures within our within our
nucleus within the the the cell has a
nucleus where all your DNA, all your
genes are kept. And there's these
different structures within that nucleus
that keep DNA and genes
uh we'll say organized.
And
the proteins that control that
organization of the DNA and the the
genes are these histone deacet
deacetylases and these acetylase
enzymes. So they'll add what are known
as acetal groups or acetal tags to these
different structures and that will
change the organization of the genes
within the uh nucleus. Okay. So why does
that matter? Well, it matters because if
the cancer cell is trying to
bind or close particular genes. So, if
it's trying to bind and express or lead
to more production of particular
proteins, it has to have access to
particular genes that allow for the
production of these proteins. Think of
like progrowth proteins.
And
what butyrate does is it will close
those genes so that the cancer cell
can't access its own genetic
information.
So it cannot produce more of those
progrowth proteins. The other side of it
is that it can encourage it can open up
the genes that are anti-cancerous and
can lead to cell death, which cancer has
a number of different ways that it can
stop cell death because obviously it
doesn't want cell death. Why would it?
It's cancer, so it's it's trying to grow
as rapidly as possible.
And when I say it's trying or it's doing
or all that stuff, just know that cancer
cells aren't thinking about this stuff.
I'm just kind of speaking in a little
bit more plain language even though it
may not seem like it. So just know that
the cancer is just reacting
biochemically in a certain particular
way. So in this situation
the butyrate could be opening the genes
that are anti-cancerous
and a perfect example of that would be I
don't know if I discussed that maybe I
discussed this in the insider uh
analysis doesn't matter the they they
may produce more of particular proteins
called BCL proteins these BCL proteins
will uh essentially allow
mitochondria to die and if you have mass
mitochondrial death then the cell
destabilizes and ultimately you get cell
death. So butyrate encourages a lot of
the anti-cancer genes to be produced
into proteins and it cuts down or or
shrinks closes up makes it more
difficult for cancer cells to access the
procancerous genes or the genes that
would be more attributed to to cell
growth. So that's the mechanism by which
butyrate uh functions.
Now in addition to that the
concentration gradient if we go back to
this crypt so again the intestinal crypt
at the bottom of the crypt there's lower
butyrate levels at the top of the crypt
there tends to be higher butyrate
concentration and the idea behind that
is that the butyrate can also have a
dual function in that it can also
encourage the production of more healthy
colonocytes healthy uh intestinal cells
while at the same time inhibiting the
cancer cells that would otherwise be
growing in that region.
There's a lot more that especially some
nuances like the different types of
cancer. I don't want to jump to the
conclusion that this would apply to all
cancers. We do have evidence that
butyrate helps against other cancers as
well, but what this study focused on was
specifically colon cancer.
And there's certainly more intricacies
to the topic than just, oh, I'm going to
up my butyrate and then therefore I'll
be cured of colon cancer. I I don't want
that to be the message. But there's no
doubt that there is a growing body of
literature which is already pretty
steadfast saying that butyrate will at
least help fight against colon cancer.
So I thought that that study was really
remarkable. um and especially when they
dove into the different mechanisms and
the different concentration gradients
and started getting into all those
details. I thought it was uh really
really incredible
uh in terms of how can you increase your
butyrate levels. I guess I'll quick talk
quick mention. So, you can
take like some people were saying, well,
I'll just eat more butter uh because
that has butyrate in it. And as far as
I'm understanding, that is true. Uh so,
there are many foods that contain
butyrate and especially fatty foods that
contain butyrate. The problem with that
is that you might be I don't know what
the expression is, but you're
stealing from the piper to pay the
popper or something along those lines.
It's the point is that there are
consequences.
So in in some situations with particular
foods like yeah you might be helping you
might be increasing your butyrate
concentration but then you're also in
increasing the concentration of many
other molecules that you may not want.
And as an example for butter you might
be increasing like steeric acid or
palmitic acid which are two saturated
fats. Butyrate is also a saturated fat
butyrate has been consistently linked to
a lot of positive effects while steic
acid and definitely I'll say at least
pelvic acid uh have been linked has been
linked to more negative uh health
outcomes.
So yeah, you could get butyrate from
other sources. And I kept, you know,
seeing that comment, well then I'll just
eat more of butter or I'll eat more of
this other thing. And I mean, yes, like
technically, yes, that would increase
butyrate, but you also have to consider
the other consequences that come with
that, the other molecules. You're not
just producing butyrate or you're not
just consuming butyrate plus other
beneficial molecules. You're consuming
butyrate, which is beneficial, plus some
potentially detrimental molecule. So,
there's a lot to say there. and you know
having an analysis on each single food
is is completely overwhelming. So the
the most direct way to get butyrate
other than supplementation is to consume
fibrous foods. And I've said this many
times before, but fibrous foods get
taken up by microbes and those get then
get converted to these different short-
chain fats. And it is true that not all
of the short- chain fats that get
produced are necessarily butyrate, but
it doesn't really matter because many of
the other short- chain fats
show benefit
uh on our health. So even if it's not
butyrate specifically, you are going to
be increasing other molecules alongside
with butyrate that also have positive
health effects unlike what we just
talked about. So fiber and not to
mention that fiber has a consistent
association I actually covered that
recently as well that fiber has a
consistent association with improvements
in cancer. So preventing cancer across a
number of different cancers and this has
been repeated across uh many many
different studies. So we have a strong
basis of literature indicating that
fiber and we know that fiber gets
converted to butyrate and we know that
butyrate has these positive effects not
just in this study but other studies as
well. So that's why I'm focusing on
fiber as opposed to other sources of
butyrate which may also come with uh
undesired other molecules.
Okay, let's get into some comments. And
I remember I had one uh comment that
strongly disagreed with uh what I
presented. So I wanted to cover that one
at least to the best of my ability here.
All right, the first comment is from
Bill Davidson. He said, "My father
always told me to eat lots of garlic and
onions. I always thought it was to
attract the ladies, but now I know the
real reason. Thanks." Because I'd
mentioned uh high doses, not cooking
doses, but uh actual like much higher
doses of garlic and onion uh have been
shown to increase butyrate levels.
So, I will say, Bill, I'm not sure who
would have said garlic and onions was
going to attract the ladies,
but either way, I'm glad that uh I'm
glad that the video and you know,
finding sources of butyrate is going to
be an overall benefit uh to to you.
Thanks for the comment.
Um the
another comment that I received which
was quite lengthy so bear with me. um
was from Wellington Amaral, PhD. So a
PhD of some sort. I don't know in what
field. Maybe this field. Who knows? Uh
but he wrote uh a few comments.
So one, legumes and roots. So this is
from this uh from Wellington. I'm going
to abbreviate Wellington. Uh from
Wellington. Legumes and roots like beans
and potatoes when cooked and you don't
want to eat them uncooked are high
glycemic. So glycemic index.
The glucose from these foods will
overpower the effect of the fat
metabolism in cancer.
I'm going to come back to address these
comments in just a second. I'm going to
go through them um and then I'll I'll
read what I responded and then I'll
maybe add a little bit more commentary.
Number two, butyrate produced by
bacteria is produced in fairly low
amounts even among people who host ideal
gut bacteria to produce it. Plus a lot
of it will be consumed by the gut cells.
Number three in cancer consuming and
thriving in fats. So in cancers
consuming fats because there are cancers
that uh take up fats. These are
experiments done in a dish and usually
where the cells are soaked in insulin
which is uh commonly added in in vitro
cell cell culture. So in vitro meaning
the cells are in a dish
uh so that the cells survive in a dish.
So Wellington is saying that the
researchers add insulin to cancer cells.
Even though these cancer cells use fat
for for energy, they're given insulin to
help them survive in a dish. Enough uh
insulin and the cells, even cancer
cells, will feed on anything, really
anything. Number four,
uh just to be clear, there's seven of
these. Number four, there is another
molecule that is very similar to
butyrate produced by gut bacteria that
doesn't depend on fiber. That's beta
hydroxybutyrate produced in the liver
from
they wrote fast metabolism fat or
fasting metabolism will produce beta
hydroxybutyrate. So I'll just adapt and
add a little bit to that. uh it can be
produced in much larger amounts in the
body and will reach the cancer wherever
it is. Number five, beta hydroxybutyrate
is also produced through dietary
manipulation. So ketogenic diet. So it's
a highfat, low glycemic carb, moderate
protein or prolonged fasting, usually
over a day or two for most people. And
there are some fats that are more easily
processed by the liver into beta
hydroxybutyrate like MCT. to mediumchain
triglycerides from coconut oil for
instance.
Number six, there is a concept or
calculation that can be easily done at
home based on the ratio of glucose to
ketone as an index. So the GKI,
that's the glucose ketone index that can
indicate the range or ratio where beta
hydroxybutyrate is likely having a
therapeutic effect on cancer in a living
human body. Beta hydroxybutyrate is one
of the three ketone bodies produced from
fat metabolism.
And finally, the Warberg effect to
explain that. Well, okay, actually he
explains it. So, I'll read what he says.
Uh Warberg effect explains that cells
shift their metabolism into fermentation
compared to regular cells because of
faulty mitochondrial oxidative
metabolism. I'm gonna pause right there
because
I'm I'm having flashbacks to when I was
trying to understand some of these
words. So what the Warberg effect is
describing which was discovered over 100
years ago at this point is that cancer
cells many cancer cells will prefer
using glucose or sugar. remember my
definition of sugar uh from before
for energy and for other reasons again
that I won't go into for the time being
because
they don't or can't use fat for energy
because their mitochondria are somehow
defunct. So therefore they strongly
prefer using glucose
sugar over fat.
And that's what he's talking about.
Mitochondrial oxidative metabolism is
the fat metabolism and fermentation is
the glucose metabolism. Hence why cancer
cells, going back to what he said, hence
why cancer cells are so hungry for
sugar, glucose, and why they're so good
at grabbing it from the blood before
healthy cells. There are amino acids
from proteins that are also fermentable
like glutamine among others. It is it's
in every food and one can't just not eat
it. Hence, there is a suggestion that
blocking cancer's use of these
fermentable amino acids pharmaceutically
in conjunction with a generic diet may
be necessary to kill cancer cells. But
patient populations see at least
temporary a few years delay or
regression in cancer progression just in
a welldesigned
mentioned diet. So, talking about
ketogenic diet,
uh, there are more factors to be
considered, but this is enough. Probably
too much for a comment. No, I I thought
that was really great, and I'm glad
you're very thoughtful about it. Um,
look up ketosis. Um, definitely well
aware of ketosis considering I described
it in the in my material. Um, and cancer
research by uh Dr. Thomas Seaff freed
Dominic Dagghastino
um and others will come up in the in the
search. Sorry for the interruption, Doc.
Uh this should render material for at
least a couple more videos. That's
certainly true. Uh have fun with it and
nice work on the educational videos. So
thank you first of all. Thank you. I
really appreciate it. Um I'm very well
aware of Dr. Seaff Freed's research as
well as Dr. Dagustinino's research. I
actually met Dr. Dagustinino uh briefly
uh earlier this year uh in person at a
conference,
but let's uh so I'm going to go through
my response and then I'm going to add in
a few details
um because I thought that there were
several things in the comment that were
incorrect and I did double check a lot
of this stuff uh just to make sure that
I wasn't, you
spewing BS. So, uh, my response to
Wellington was, well, thanks for the
comments, Wellington. I'm puzzled by
some of them, though, which I was. For
example, legumes are not high glycemic.
They're not. Uh, I suppose you could
argue that they are compared to fats,
but that's not actually how the glycemic
index or the glycemic load are compared.
Uh, glycemic index is speaking to
carbohydrates, so not talking about
fats. Um, I'm also confused on your
points about low butyrate production by
ideal bacteria considering that the
majority of our butyrate comes from the
microbiome. And then I looked up some
numbers around 50 to 100 micro mole per
day. Um, mill mole mill mole per day.
That's a big difference. Uh it's true
that we absorb less but even so the
amount consumed absorbed is consistently
linked to have a biological effect
especially around the liver and the
portal vein because that's the first
point of interaction for whatever is
absorbed uh by the body from the
intestines.
Uh I actually have more videos releasing
on that soon. So I do have more uh I did
have another one coming out on butyrate.
So that released that was on the immune
system. Not sure I agree on all cancer
research being done in dishes where
cancer cells are soaked in insulin. Uh
in fact I know that from firsthand
experience considering that I worked
with cancer cells and didn't use
insulin. Uh here's an example of fat
consuming cancer cells not exposed to
insulin includes an invivo research. It
even shows beta hydroxybutyrate
signaling uh cancer growth and then I
supplied a study number. Uh I agree
about beta hydroxybutyrate.
I have content on that too. I'm also
familiar with Dr. Seaff Freed's work. I
have a video on his work and plan on
doing some others time permitting. Uh I
definitely need to cover that more
extensively. I think his uh work is
intriguing and seems to have some great
arguments, but it also doesn't account
for many other considerations brought up
by cancer re by the cancer research
community. Anyway, I plan on covering
more on the ketogenic diet and cancer in
the future. It's a fascinating area of
research and I wish I could get uh more
more into it and flesh it out more.
Yeah. Again, thanks for the for the
comments. Um again, I I don't actually
agree with some of the
the comments here.
Uh
and I've heard almost all of them before
from other people. Um the point being
that
while we focus so much on
cancer research and just this this idea
that all cancers just use glucose and
that they have a complete inability to
shift to fat metabolism. Um that hasn't
been what I've seen in the lab when I
was doing my PhD because actually
initially I was doing some metabolism
work. I ended up doing some metabolism
work, but I was doing some metabolism
work where I had switched
cancer cells to using more fat
metabolism. And it is true that they
didn't grow nearly as quickly, nearly as
well, but that also doesn't mean that
they ended up dying off um when switched
over to fat. Now, it is true also that I
did not restrict. So, part of Dr. Seaf
Freed's ideas as far as I understand it
is that you would restrict glucose
to the cancer cells but in addition to
that you would also restrict their
glutamine which is what uh Amaral
Wellington mentioned that you use a
pharmaceutical to stop glutamine in the
mitochondrian and you also stop the
cancer cells from being able to rely on
glucose and therefore it stress resses
them to such a degree because they can't
use fat in this instance that they end
up dying and it is there is when I did
do a video on this maybe two years ago a
year and a half ago and I covered some
of the aspects of Dr. Seaf Freed's work.
I went through multiple of his reviews
and some of his papers and whatnot. And
then I also presented the other
counterargument
and in that I brought up that there are
studies looking at cancer cells that uh
prefer to use fat metabolism. And I'm
not sure I think Dr. Seafood may have
changed his stance just slightly, just
shifted it. Don't quote me on this, but
my understanding is that there well I
know for a fact that there are cancers
that do only or I shouldn't say only uh
primarily use fat metabolism to sustain
themselves.
That doesn't mean that there aren't many
cancers that use glucose for energy. Now
the exact reason for that is I think
debated from and again I just need to
preface this. I need to look more into
that literature. I have looked into it
some. Um there's arguments that it is a
mutation burden as in the cells are
unable to produce the requisite enzymes
or whatever it might be to to shift over
to fat metabolism. Um or that there are
there's damage or morphological changes
that happen within mitochondria. And Dr.
Seaf Freed offers some images when you
look at some of the mitochondria. the
inside of the mitochondria called the
christe is either damaged like
completely havoc has been wre
um
on the uh the inside of the
mitochondrian or it just doesn't exist.
Uh which speaks to the potential effect
that
metabolism could have in these uh cancer
cells. So there's a ton to say here. I
just don't think that I would boil it
down to as simply as well people just
need to jump on a ketogenic diet and
restrict their glutamine potentially
through pharmaceutical means. That would
probably be the only way and then you'll
just be able to cure cancer. That seems
to be an explanation that keeps being
brought up. People keep saying, "Oh,
just check out Dr. Seaff's work." I
don't think people understand that Dr.
seafoods work. It's not just like it's
not like the establishment is just like,
"Oh yeah, screw that guy." Um there
there are legitimate
many many many many studies that show
convincing evidence of the mutation
burden
being a causitive factor for cancer that
I will say that when I looked at Dr.
Seaff Freed's work, I also found some
really credible and great research
indicating that he had some great
points. So, in my video at the time, I
kind of fell in between and I said,
well, why why couldn't it be both? Why
couldn't we have kind of a hybrid model
that indicates that for some cancers,
yeah, there's a there's defunct
mitochondria and we could be be able to
target those and effectively really
inhibit and damage those and and and
kill those types of cancer. While on the
other side, we still also have other
cancers that aren't as susceptible to
just metabolic reprogramming. um that
they're they're able to kind of shift
from, you know, glucose to fat or maybe
they're predominantly in fat metabolism
or whatever it might be. So,
I'm just I just don't think that it's
quite as simplistic as to just say uh
yeah, just eat a ketogenic diet or fast,
get your beta hydroxybutyrate levels,
which is a the main ketone that we
discuss, and therefore you'll be able to
kill all cancer cells.
I understand the point that it goes to
different like you can get that those
ketones to different areas of the body
more efficiently. That might be true. Um
but I will say that there's other
research as well that looks at butyrate
that looks at butyrate outside of
cancer. O looks at like endothelial cell
health and they do show in vivo research
where if you increase butyrate levels
that it does pass into the bloodstream
and
that it has an effect on the entire
vasculature so your cardiovascular
system and it tends to improve your
cardiovascular system. So to say that
we're we're not cons we can't get enough
butyrate to have a biologic to create a
biological difference just doesn't
really bear out in the literature. Um we
have many different types of studies
that indicate otherwise. Not to mention
I'll also fall back on the idea that the
main source of butyrate that we get so
one of the main sources fiber has been
consistently linked in many many many
studies I'm talking hundreds and
hundreds of thousands of participants
uh shown to reduce cancer
incidence and mortality and just has an
overall positive effect. So is that
necessarily through butyrate? While we
can't necessarily say that I will
concede that, but I also
can't imagine that that doesn't have an
effect, especially when we have so much
evidence specifically pointing to
butyrate having a positive effect. So,
probably a more lengthy conversation to
be had there. I agree with certain
points. Uh I just don't agree with uh
with uh certain other points. But
anyway, I still appreciate the
commentary and uh oh, and I will say for
the cancer research for sure, uh there's
plenty of invivo research where they
don't apply insulin to the cells. Uh I
don't know, like I never well, I
shouldn't say I never in one of my
experiments that was never published, I
applied insulin just to see what would
happen. And um nothing nothing crazy
happened. Um, but in all of my
experiments that were published and in
other other experiments I did just kind
of leading up uh we never used insulin
in any of my uh cell research. All
right, we got uh about three more topics
and then I'd like to just go over some
light housekeeping like I usually keep
at the end of each podcast. So for the
next topic, you know, I had to discuss
this because I discussed this earlier in
the year. I did some work on seed oils
and their impact on our health. I mostly
focused on cardiovascular health, but I
also touched on other aspects of health
as well.
So, seed oils and health.
I think the there's probably a number of
different mechanisms that people discuss
seed oils and how they affect our body
and how they're, you know, a a negative
force in our body. Um, the two that I'm
aware of at least that have been
discussed in the literature
is or yeah, okay. discussed in the
literature uh but not exactly in the
context of how it's discussed in the
anti-seed oil world is the oxidation of
polyunsaturated fats. So seed oils are
well examples are like soybean oil, corn
oil, canola oil, safflower oil,
sunflower oil. Those kinds of oils
contain within them the dangerous
component that a lot of people have
talked about linoleic acid which is an
omega-6 polyunsaturated fat. Basically
what that means is it's a fat molecule
that has multiple kinks in it and
because of its structure it
is more easily oxidized meaning that is
more easily damaged in in a manner of
speaking. So that's one aspect. The
other aspect is and then of course if
it's integrated into your cell. So think
of like into your cell membrane uh into
the the membrane of your organels like
the different structures. Think like the
mitochondrian, think of the endopplasmic
reticulum, the GGI apparatus.
Um that then you could potentially get
this accumulation of these damaged fat
molecules within the structure of your
cells, which obviously that doesn't seem
like a very positive thing.
The other thing is that omega sixes can
be pro-inflammatory.
Again, these are the mechanisms that
have been mentioned
that omega sixes can be pro-inflammatory
in that they get converted to what's
known as arachidonic acid. And that
arachidonic acid can have uh significant
negative effects within the cell. And
technically arachidonic acid is then
converted or can be converted to
different uh pro-inflam other
pro-inflammatory molecules I believe
like prostaglandins
uh icosenoids and there's a there's a
bunch of other ones as well but
ultimately these pro-inflammatory
molecules then can get secreted out of
the cell and can lead to more of an
immune reaction and and damage the
surrounding environment and things of
that nature. So, those are some of the
mechanisms that have been brought up.
I'm sure that there are others that have
probably been brought up in kind of the
depths of the internet that I'm not
aware of. Um, and that's that's
perfectly fair. I'm not here to really
discuss the mechanisms uh as much as I
am to discuss the clinical data because
ultimately the clinical data is always
going to trump any sort of mechanistic
research.
So, and I'm actually going to come back
to that point on our final topic as well
because I think that's going to be
important. Okay. So,
looking at the clinical data, I pulled
together a whole lot of studies in
total. I think it was I didn't
necessarily open up every single one of
these studies, but I opened up a lot of
different analyses, including some
isolated studies. And across something
like 200 studies, maybe 150 studies, uh,
that looked at in some capacity omega6s,
again, that's these polyunsaturated fats
and their impact on our primarily
cardiovascular health, but again, I I
did dabble in some of the other metrics
outcomes as well.
It showed pretty
reliably
that there was either a neutral effect
or a slight positive effect of consuming
omega-6 fats.
Now there is one research group that
seems to believe differently from many
other research groups especially one
research group uh headed by uh a
prominent researcher known as Bill
Harris. Um, this one research group, the
Ramsden group, ended up doing an
analysis that I thought was quite
interesting where they split omega6
consumption,
the studies that just looked at omega6
consumption versus a control group
versus the studies that looked at omega6
plus omega-3 versus a control. And they
showed that if you just looked at the
studies that
gave people omega-6 fats to consume
that they tended to have more
cardiovascular disease.
But if you looked at the studies that
used omega 6 plus omega-3,
they did not show that link anymore. So
then the the main point there that the
omega sixs may be a negative if omega-3s
are not in the conversation as well. Now
I did have some
negative things to say about
the details of their analysis that I'm
not going to rehash here. Um, I think
that they missed the boat or they left
out certain details and didn't do proper
uh analysis on some of the data that
once you open up the studies, you
realize, oh, well, I I don't know why
they didn't include this or why they
didn't, you know, account for that or
whatever it might be. Again, for the
details, check out the video. I I'll
have it linked for you. Um, but there
were several things I just didn't agree
with their overall interpretation based
off the data that was presented.
Still, that doesn't mean that they
didn't have a point. And in certain
respects, I did agree with them on their
overall point, like omega 6's, like the
relationship between omega 6s and
omega-3s. There were some other analyses
that I didn't think were that great. I
think that overall there just isn't a
whole lot of data on from randomized
control trials that look at omega-6
consumption versus you know particular I
don't know like saturated fats or some
other condition. Um there are some old
studies like most of them are from like
the 60s7s
all the way up to maybe the 80s and 90s
but a lot of these studies have so many
flaws within them like in certain
respects they have strengths to them but
in other respects they have a lot of
flaws to them. Again you know check out
the video on all that. It's like a
25minute video where I go into a lot
more of this stuff and there's even more
to say than what what I went over in the
video.
But ultimately like basing any sort of
strong conclusion based on just that
data is not going to lead you to
anywhere
really.
uh and my conclusion was that and it's I
think largely true that the studies
showed either a neutral effect or the
study and there were studies that showed
a negative effect to be clear but again
if you look at some of the methodology
of those studies you you start to
realize oh well there's a lot wrong with
these studies like the these in the
modern day like if today a study was was
tried to be published in a reputable
journal they probably would not be able
to be published. It it just the peer
reviewers would be like this is insane.
You you lost 80% of your participants.
They how are you going to publish this?
Um or at least if we publish it, you're
going to have to put in a lot of
explanation for why you lost 80% of your
participants or um there's in potential
strong likelihood of inclusion of trans
fats. uh there was a lot of mixture
between the control group and the
intervention group. Like there's there's
all kinds of different problems. So
that's why I'm saying it's really hard
to sit there and look at these studies
that were done such a long time ago and
knowing the information that we know now
try to say that those studies are a good
representation of seed oils or anti-seed
oils. Um so I can't really go either
way, you know, for seed oils or
anti-seed oils. based on those studies
and when you do meta analyses looking at
all the different studies
even those meta analyses I mean largely
they show a neutral effect as in no
benefit no negative effects but even
those there's flaws simply because of
the data sets that they have to rely on
to create their conclusions so then to
take it a step further I decide to look
at what other studies have been done so
I'm looking at like huge huge largecale
uh epidemiological evidence and looking
at different controls that they do
different they try to control for
different factors. Um they'll try to do
subgroup analyses. There was one that
was really great where they not only
looked at omega sixs but also looked at
omega-3s. And not only did they look at
the the they didn't look at the
consumption, they actually looked at the
blood measurements of omega sixs and
omega-3s in the blood as well as um
proxies for tissue.
So what's actually integrated into the
body? So aside from just in the blood
which is already pretty damning but then
on top of that what's actually found in
the tissue and
there they showed a really striking
graph that as the omega6 to omega3
ratio. So that means the more omega6
so omega 6 over omega3. So taking both
into consideration,
if you have more omega-6 or reduced
levels of omega-3 that there is an
increased risk of cardiovascular
disease, which goes back to what the
Ramston group was saying that if you
just up omega sixs that you get worse
outcomes. Now again that was based on
old data that had a lot of flaws in it.
But now if we look at the ep this
epidemiological study that included uh
tens of thousands of participants and
used far more rigorous metrics of using
blood measurements.
They do show a kind of a similar story
that if you increase omega sixs in the
blood to such a degree that the ratio is
is so much in favor of omega sixs over
omega-3s that you start to see this
association with increased risk of
cardiovascular disease. Okay. So that in
itself is is pretty alarming and it's
it's kind of scary. But if you look at
the numbers, so the ratio, the what they
considered the ideal ratio or what they
compared everything against was a ratio
of four. So for four units of omega
sixs, you have one unit of omega 3.
Okay? And then they scaled that. So, as
people had more and more and more and
more omega sixs, so we're getting to 12,
15, 20 times the amount of omega sixes
in the blood compared to omega-3s, they
showed that the risk increased,
increased, increased. Okay, so keeping
that in mind, then they were like, well,
what does the typical population
consume? So we've got our ideal of four
to one, but what does the ideal
population consume? And I think it was
something like 8:1, 9:1, 10:1, something
like that. So certainly more, but when
you look at that same graph, it is still
squarely in reduced risk and really the
best interpretation would be no reduced
or no no increased risk. So right there,
neutral risk as in no negative effects
that are experienced from typical
consumption. And keep in mind, this is
typical consumption, which means that
people in day-today living are consuming
omega sixs and the result is this
association with no increased risk. So
yes, we are talking about including
people that are going for fast food.
Yes, we are talking about people that
are cooking at home. Yes, we're talking
about people that are going out to fine
dining establishments that are eating
junk food that are it's it's tens of
thousands of people. So, we're including
all these people. We're talking about
heated seed oils. We're talking about
cold seed oils. We're talking about all
these situations
because we have such a large data pool
and the result is that there is no
relationship with increased
cardiovascular disease. Now, let me take
a step back from that and let I just
said that we're looking at people, you
know, that go fine dining that may be
consuming omega sixes, that go fast
food, all that stuff that may be eating
heated seed oils and cold seed oils.
That doesn't mean that we have the
granularity
through subgroup analyses to find out if
one group may be getting disastrous
consequences from consuming seed oils
while another group is consuming seed
oils and getting benefit from seed oils
and that's what's leading to a neutral
effect. Hopefully that's clear.
We're looking at big data sets. So we
would need to do far more analysis on
these different subgroups to tease out
is that neutral effect or that neutral
association is that
still the case when we look at these
different subgroups. Is it neutral for
everyone or is it maybe slightly
elevated for some people and then
slightly reduced for other people? you
know those answers were not provided in
that study. But one other thing that
they did, I mentioned this in my insider
analysis
that
if
they looked at just omega-3 consumption
or they just looked at omega6
consumption as they did a a standardized
increase in I guess I shouldn't say
consumption but the blood levels as they
did a standardized increase in blood
levels of omega-3s and standardized
increase in blood levels of omega sixes.
So breaking the data apart, not looking
at the ratio, but looking at just the
amount found in the blood, they found
that no matter what, there was either a
neutral or reduced risk in the omega6
group and there was only a reduced risk
in the omega-3 group. So when looking at
omega-3s or looking at omega sixs uh
separately. So that
would indicate that the evidence is more
leaning in the direction of omega sixes
probably are not a negative to our
health.
Does that necessarily mean we have all
the answers? No. Because of what I just
explained before. We don't have
different subgroups. Now, in addition to
that, I did do a separate analysis on
canola oil,
which isn't which is one of the the ones
that people are really fearful of for
some reason. I did a poll and people
voted on canola oil being like the
number one that they wanted me to look
into. So, I looked at canola oil and if
it's inflammatory. So, I pulled together
every single study I could find and I I
asked the community. I used the the good
old AIs uh out there to pull together
every single study, every randomized
control trial I could find on canola oil
and inflammation.
And I think I found 10. There are 10
studies currently that have been done on
canola oil and looking at inflammation.
I will be honest with you, most of these
studies, the study quality is really
bad. uh it's not very good but based on
all these studies I think nine of them
showed either neutral or positive
effects on inflammation and that's
compared against all kinds of different
things. There was one study that showed,
it wasn't a very good study as well, but
still there was one study that showed
that it may have a pro-inflammatory risk
if it was heated over and over and over
again. I think it was heated something
like 20 times over and led to small
increases in inflammation. So based off
this one
kind of poor quality study,
there might be a signal there that if
you constantly heat omega sixes or we'll
say canola oil, we restrict it to what
we looked at to canola oil. If you
continuously heat it over and over like
you know on on a pan or whatever it
might be, you continuously use it. So
think like fast food. I think that's a
great example. I don't know how the fast
food industry works in terms of I'm
assuming they don't rotate out the oil
after every single meal, right, that
they make. It's probably just
continuously heated over and over and
over again, which is exactly what we're
talking about here. So, in that
situation,
there may be a a small inflammatory
risk.
Keep in mind, we're not looking at
cardiovascular disease in this situation
anymore. So, we're looking at kind of a
softer metric, but still with that
softer metric, we're seeing that there
may be a negative effect. So, is it
possible that if you repeatedly heat
these omega-6 unsaturated fats,
keep in mind that's going to massively
increase the amount of oxidation that
occurs to them. Could that be a negative
to our health?
One single study looking at this is not
enough for me to say end all beall we
are for sure uh we need to cut away all
seed oils or anything like that and that
wouldn't be a reasonable conclusion
anyway based off the other all the other
data that I I told you about. But my
perspective currently is that omega
sixes at the amounts that we're
consuming them even at really high
amounts of consumption
just don't seem to be much of a risk at
least for cardiovascular disease and
also seems to be the case for uh
inflammation based on the evidence I've
seen up to now.
that could shift if you start to add in
other variables like heat the heating
process or we don't even know if
heating, you know, if you cook with it
once, who's going to sit there and save
the oil and then cook with it again and
then save the oil and then cook with it
again. You know, that's really only in
kind of a fast food situation or a
restaurant situation. So,
is that applicable to how you cook?
Probably not. So, I don't even know if
we can extend that to one time, cooking
with it one time, and if that's going to
have a negative effect. Um, I I can't
even speculate. I don't know which
direction that would go. The only thing
we know is if you cook with it 20 times
over, then there is a potential for a
negative effect. So, you can kind of see
where I'm going with this. The the
overall point for me is that omega sixs
seem to be at least neutral for our
health and likely in certain instances
slightly positive for our health.
Omega-3s
seem to be robustly continuously
positive for our health. So, if you're
really afraid of it, just make sure just
don't worry about your omega sixes as
much and then increase your omega-3s a
little bit and then you'll fall right in
line with what the research indicates
that you'll you'll be you'll see
positive effects on your health. Um, and
there's a lot of nuance to that as well
because, you know, if you're over
consuming all this stuff and you're
gaining weight, well, hold on. you know,
we got to back off and we can't say
then, oh,
well, Nick is misleading us because
omega six's uh made me, you know, gain
weight or I had a heart attack when I
started consuming more omega sixs. It's
like, well, hold on, you also gain 30
pounds. So, is it the omega sixes or is
it the weight gain? like you know
there's that's why I'm saying there's
there's a lot of nuances that on an
individual level you would have to
figure out but on the broad strokes
that's what I'm saying is that typically
there's a neutral to slightly uh
improvement in health from omega sixs
and omega-3s there seems to be a
consistent improvement in health
subgroups we still need to to look into
that in more depth I'm trying to
communicate this as intellectually
honest as possible
I'm sure I'll get called some seed oil
shill by any number of different people.
Um, that's fine.
But
that's really where I ended up uh
landing
based off of uh my video. And I would
certainly recommend that you uh check
out uh the the video because I do a far
more succinct job of explaining uh
everything I just went over. Okay, let's
get into a few comments here.
Uh, Oki Okitasuji
says, "What I find curious is why all
seed oils are lumped together
considering their fatty acid composition
is quite different." So, what Oki is
talking about here is that I'd mentioned
that there's uh
soybean, corn, canola, safflower,
sunflower oils, you know, etc.
And it's true that each one of those has
a different composition. Like canola is
pretty different from the others. And
yet people seem to be most fearful of
canola. Uh but then if you were to look
at some of these others, there's some
more similarity, but there's still uh
differences in the type of fat molecule
that's found. So just because we're
talking about omega sixes, there are
different types of omega sixs as well. I
think the main one that people are
afraid of is linoleic acid.
So, it's true. We're lumping all seed
oils together. And it kind of speaks to
kind of the imprecision of how this is
being, you know, talked about. And if I
had it my way, I would break each seed
oil apart. I would break each fatty acid
apart, the percentages of each, the
absolute amounts of each. I would look
at different outcomes for each
inflammation, cardiovascular disease,
cancer, diabetes risk, all these
different things. I would look at
subgroups. I would look at which ones
have been heated, which ones are cold,
like all that all that information,
which would, you know, it only take me
about a year or two years worth of work.
And in addition to that, uh we don't
have some of that data. So,
it's a great point. Uh it's just
unfortunately again in the social media
landscape people just love to
oversimplify which leads to to a lot of
uh I think just in general bad takes.
Another question from Tropeus or not
question uh comment. My main takeaway,
even if seed oils are bad, the effect
size is so hard to find and easily
confounded that I'm probably reducing my
lifespan just stressing about it.
Yeah, that's true. Uh people are so
focused on seed oils that they're kind
of missing the
forest for the trees. I think I nailed
that one. Uh yeah, focusing on so many
other things is going to have a far
greater impact on your your life and
your longevity, your health span, uh
focusing on seed oils, especially based
off the literature that we have at this
point. Another comment, water balloon
fighter. Uh thank you so much for this
and for highlighting the importance of
what are you replacing X nutrient with?
as a dietitian, that's always something
I'm keen on asking patients. Not sure if
you remember uh since you have many
subscribers, but I recently commented
that your work was part of my
inspiration to apply for a masters of
science in health statistics and I just
got accepted. Uh so I did I did uh
comment under this one. I just want to
say again congratulations. I mean that's
that's really awesome. Um I think
statistics is just such an incredible
field. I've I've always hated math. Uh
I've hated math. I hate math. But that
said,
statistics for some reason is just like
conceptually is just something that I
understand far better than the actual
mathematical formulas. Uh and I think
statistics is just such an incredible
field that's I think it's often mi
misaligned
uh malaligned.
Maligned. There we go. Woo. got to the
word eventually. English is also a
struggle at the moment. Um, yeah, it's
it's an area that's often maligned. Uh,
people will say kind of pathy comments
like, uh, you know, you can you can
massage the data however you want. Um,
you know,
any number of different things. I can't
think of them off the top of my head.
I'm not the quickest uh quickest on my
feet, but um it's but to me, I think
it's just an area that
if you can understand it, you can have a
lot of respect for it and it will help
you a lot in understanding
a lot of the world around you and what
are the odds of something happening or
or especially since you're going into
you said health uh statistics, you'll be
able to learn a lot more about the
epidemiology. ology you'll be able to
understand more about biostistics
looking at you know when you should be
using proper statistical analyses like
uh tests or student t test one-way test
two-way t tests looking at uh anovas
bonferonia adjustments like there's
there's all these different things that
uh you learn about and they make a big
difference because once once you start
reading uh studies you're like oh And I
see why they did this statistical test
because if they'd used this other more
common method, it would have given them
a potentially faulty
uh conclusion. Or you'll read a study
and you're like, "Oh man, they really
it's so like the study is so welld
designed, but unfortunately they use the
wrong statistical test which really
makes the conclusion of the study uh
basically null and void." So as you
delve into that world, it it really
gives you a greater appreciation for uh
for study design and um and yeah, just
uh just health in general. So yeah,
congrats. And you already being a
dietitian and then adding health
statistics on top of that, that's going
to be uh it's going to be a potent
combination. I think I've taken four
statistics courses. I think two in
undergrad and then oh no maybe five
maybe five or six even and then I've
taken multiple in grad school and I
still have so much more to learn. Um
it's it's a it's a huge field. Uh I'm
never going to be at the level that you
probably will be uh as you know getting
your masters in biostatistitian
being a biostistician and whatnot but um
it's it's an incredible field. Anyway, I
won't uh bore people with it anymore,
but I just want to say congrats. That
really is a huge thing in terms of u
what are you replacing X nutrient with?
Yeah, that's a big thing, too. I think
one point that I was trying to make in
in my analysis is like we have so much
evidence implicating, for example, like
saturated fats and especially trans fats
as being a negative for our health. Uh
saturated fat, I'm talking about an
umbrella term. There's many
subcategories of saturated fat that, you
know, some are actually beneficial for
our health, some are negative for our
health, but I'm talking about the
negative ones. So, if you were to
replace these seed oils with this
narrative that seed oils are killing us,
all this stuff, and then you replace
that with like trans fats, well,
regardless of what you think about seed
oils, you have just va just massively
increased your risk of death uh by
switching over to trans fat. So what are
you sub substituting a particular food
for or particular type of food for? That
is an incredibly important question in
the real world. Uh I mean you know this
right as a dietitian. You know this
better than I do as a dietician. Um that
it can have massive impact on your life.
So, we shouldn't get so caught up in
kind of the social media sphere and
world uh where people are are just
scaring you with kind of nonsense. I
mean like a lot of this stuff they just
uh they they often don't site studies or
they'll site a single study but then
they if you if you go into like chat GPT
or you go into like any of these AI
systems don't necessarily ask them uh
are seed oils good for me because you
know they're going to come back and then
if you have the mentality of like the
establishment they've they've
indoctrinated the the doctors and all
that stuff that's fine
but ask a question like list all the
seed oil studies that have been done or
list the ones that have been done the
last five years and then look at like
I'm not saying that this is the the only
barometer because really you should have
somebody that's like going to go through
all these studies but
look at the conclusion for most of these
studies and you'll be surprised I mean
how many studies just consistently show
positive or at least neutral effects of
seed oil consumption or omega-6
consumption, linoleic acid consumption,
and then you go to these fear-mongering
like social media platforms,
and you have to ask yourself at a
certain point, why are they not covering
any of these studies? Why are they
they're so adamant that omega sixes and
seed oils in general are so negative for
our health? But then there you you will
find 20 30 50 100 studies from all these
different seed oils and the vast
majority of them say positive effects
from all different types of labs across
different countries, different funding
agencies, all that stuff. It just it
just kind of has to hit you and think
like why are they saying that exactly?
Like, can I trust these people if
they're not going to address I I
understand them not knowing about a
particular study or even particular two
or three studies. I'm not talking about
that. I'm talking about the vast
majority of the studies indicate no
harm.
So, anyway, I'm kind of going off on a
tangent there, but I just something I
just wanted to point out. But again,
just want to say congrats. And yes, as a
listener, you should be thinking about
what am I going to be substituting my
omega-6 with? If I want to avoid omega
sixs, what am I going to substitute that
with? Is it more protein? Okay, that
might be good. Uh would it be a fibrous
carbohydrate? Okay, that might be good.
Is it uh potentially more palmitic acid
fil saturated fat or is it trans fat?
that's probably not a good idea. So, you
should always think about what you're
going to be substituting it for. All
right, the second to last topic that I
wanted to cover is the ineffectiveness
of creatine.
I've done so many videos and I plan on
doing so many more on creatine because
there's so much research that's been
done on creatine. But there was this one
study that came out from some pretty
reputable uh researchers
that
they social media I shouldn't say social
media media I actually saw media
covering this uh saying that
actually let me backtrack real quick.
Social media largely said that creatine
was still beneficial after this study.
So, this stud this study essentially
says that creatine is ineffective. And
I'll explain what that means in just a
little bit, but social media
went in on this study and said, "No,
they messed all this stuff up." Which
they they did mess up some things. I'm
going to go over it in just a second.
But I always find it funny that once
we've kind of globbed on, we've attached
ourselves to something, creatine is
beneficial, which I am definitely in
that camp.
But it's almost like we have to it's
like our preconceived notion immediately
when we get hit with a study that says
something different, we have the only
thing we focus on is what are the
negatives of that study. as if there are
there there's no way that we
we shouldn't be like trying to integrate
this study with what the broader
literature has to say. The only thing we
do is just go in on that study. It's
like you go in angry already. It's like
going into a conversation angry as
opposed to going into a conversation
with, okay, let me ask questions first
before I start accusing. And in social
media, creatine is kind of elevated up
to this point of like it's untouchable.
So all the all the all the videos I saw,
they weren't even necessarily critical
uh analyses of like the study design and
whatnot, they were just like this study
is just like BS. Like ah, you know,
they're talking nonsense. You know, it's
it it was like this pre again this
preconceived notion of like we've
accepted creatine into our ranks,
therefore everything against it is just
nonsense. Um,
which is uh which is tough to fight
against, but it's definitely something
that we all have to kind of be aware of.
Definitely myself included. Um anyway,
so beside that there's this this
creatine study that released several
months ago at this point and they were
looking at lean mass. So creatine has
been known that if you consume it that
it increases lean mass. It's been shown
across a whole host of different
studies. But what this study did that
was unique was they had participants
load with creatine. So they took
creatine and they were compared against
the placebo group, but the they took
their lean mass measurements by a DEXA
scan uh before they took creatine. Then
they took another DEXA scan 7 days later
after they'd loaded with creatine.
They had been consuming creatine for 7
days. And then they underwent a
resistance training program for 12 weeks
after that. Um, and then they compared
against the placebo group that also
underwent a resistance training program
for 12 weeks. And then they measured
their lean body mass again. And what
they showed is that yes, their lean body
mass was increased at the end of 12
weeks, but if you subtracted the initial
seven days, so after the first seven
days of creatine loading, if you took
that
added lean mass that they they gained
from the creatine supplementation
because creatine leads to water weight
gain, there was a nullified effect of
the lean mass gain. Meaning in simple
terms that the creatine, the only thing
it was doing was increasing water weight
and that all the previous research was
faulty because they had falsely assumed
that the increases in lean mass at the
end of all their studies was because
creatine was leading to greater muscle
growth.
Okay. So in one way that's this study
was really I I liked it. It was very
simple design. I really appreciated the
fact that they did this style where they
they didn't actually start resistance
training until after the first seven
days of loading with the placebo or the
creatine. And then the fact that they're
able to tell the difference between the
creatine at the end and the creatine
after the seven days to try to tease out
those differences and found, oh, there's
no difference. they all the the the the
gain over those 12 weeks is not from
anything that happened over those 12
weeks. It's from the first seven days,
the water weight. So, that is definitely
on the surface it seems like a pretty
damning study. And it's it's not that
the other studies were like
I don't know mischievous in any way or
anything like that. They were just they
just had an error in their methodology.
But the real thing is, did they really?
And here's where I came back with some
critiques of the this new studies
designed. One major critique that I had
is that they actually clamped the
volume. Uh so from the the weight
lifted. So over those 12 weeks, the
resistance training was the exact same
between the placebo and the creatine.
Now, if you know anything about
creatine, you know the creatine
mechanism of action is that it increases
the energy available to continue to lift
weights. So if you are clamped at the
amount of weight that you can lift
throughout that 12 weeks. So the volume
the total amount of work done is the
same then you are and this is a major
issue in epidemiology as in not not a
major issue as in like many studies
suffer from this but they they're very
aware of this problem. you are removing
the the main benefit of creatine and
then saying look creatine doesn't work.
So what what would be a better design
is to not keep the volume the same, but
to allow the creatine group to if they
were to get this benefit of added volume
just because they can do more added
volume then measure if they see any
improvements in in lean mass. And
I think and it's not just that I think
it's not this is just like some bias
like because I'm a big fan of creatine
I'm going to defend creatine. There's
also an aspect of there are other
studies that have done that and they
have shown that if you increase the
volume.
Sure enough creatine leads to actual
muscle gain over the placebo group. Now
in addition to that
there are studies that have not looked
at lean mass and looked at a far more
specific far more targeted measure of
the actual proteins within the muscle.
So the problem with lean mass is that
you're measuring yes muscle mass but
you're also measuring bone mass and
you're measuring uh cartilage or
connective tissue. And that's not to say
that bone mass is going to change over
you know 12 weeks 16 weeks or whatever
it might be even I don't know three
month well three months 12 weeks uh like
6 months it probably wouldn't change any
appreciable amount um but what might
change is like their cartilage or
whatever it might be would it be enough
to account for everything that we saw
probably not but is lean mass sensitive
enough to pick up small differences is
between the placebo group and the
creatine group especially when you clamp
the amount of volume. But even if we
take that aside, the answer is
potentially not. So we don't know the
answer to that. But what we do know is
that there are studies that have not
have just foregone the the the lean mass
and looked at the actual proteins. So
the actual measin and the uh actin
protein. So these are the actual
filamental proteins that allow your
musculature to move. They actually
ratchet back and forth. It's an
incredible process. Um, you can look up
crossbridge cycling and you'll you'll
learn how incredible it is. But anyway,
when studies look at those, they show
pretty substantial increases in those
proteins from just creatine
supplementation. So yes, creatine
has a direct effect on the musculature.
Yes, it does fill it with water as well.
So that is well known, no debating that.
But this study, while it was
illuminating in in one regard, and it
kind of set off yellow flags of like,
hey, in the future, maybe when we look
at lean mass, we should measure after
the initial 7 days of creatine
supplementation, which I think is a is a
great contribution to the field. But on
the other hand, is it damnation of
creatine? No.
and my creatine sponsor would be pissed
if I said yes. No, I'm just kidding. Um,
so I still remain obviously in
incredibly bullish about creatine.
Again, it's a supplement. Is it going to
change a person's world? Maybe if they
have some sort of creatine deficiency or
something like that. But like for the
vast majority of people, it's just going
to be a small benefit just like any
other supplement that's out there. Um,
as far as I'm aware, I I like creatine
simply because it has an effect on the
brain, has an effect on performance, has
an effect on our musculature, has an
effect on a number of different areas.
Sleep, uh, and there's there's even more
research coming out that I'll get into
in the future. So, is it a debunking of
creatine? No, it's more of a cautionary
tale, and I think it's a it's a good one
to have. Um, but it doesn't negate any
of the far more specific, far more
nuanced research that's been done out
there that people just aren't aware of.
So anyway, wanted to throw that out
there just because I thought it was
fascinating.
Okay, so some comments.
Yeah, I actually wanted to add this.
This is one of my comments. I said just
as a fun aside for those that uh that uh
put up unending emphasis on who funded
the study. So this study that showed
that creatine was ineffective.
One of the main researchers of the study
has a sponsorship with a creatine
producing company and yet they still
publish a study against creatine. And
this is not the first time that I've
seen this. actually multiple times I've
seen when I look at the funding source
and it's by somebody who is funded by
like a creatine company or there's one
that was on Tongat Aliyah I think and
the study was actually maybe even
performed by Tongat Ali company and they
published results that showed that there
was no effect now is that like a is a
constant thing a common thing no it's
not and that's why we need uh systems
like what's known as clinical trials.gov
uh which forces researchers to
pre-register what they're going to
measure and then to submit their data
regardless of if they publish or if they
don't publish. And clinicaltrials.gov is
just a fantastic website. So
I thought that was it's still funny
though like when you know people get so
strung up on you just got to focus on
funding. If the funding is wrong, then
I'm just dismissing the study when there
are many instances, probably not as many
as there probably should be, but there
are many instances where uh the funding
funding source actually would be very
unhappy with the results of the study
and the study still gets published
because
and I've had these conversations with
some of my uh my PIs in the past, my
mentors in the past, but uh during my
you know, grad school, But there are
contracts and the university also
oversees some of the at least you know
the people I've spoken to they the
university oversees the contracts that
are that are written out and it's often
written in such a language that
regardless of the results I will publish
the results. So you have no you once you
give me the money
I will conduct the study and I will
publish the study as is. So regardless
of if it's positive or negative um and
that happens quite often. So at least
again not not necessarily something I've
done but it's uh from from insight from
some of the researchers that I've spoken
to. Okay. Anyway, back on topic. Pac-Man
Fannibal said, "Uh, more creatine for me
and anyone else who's been using it.
This study is the best way to keep the
cost down and the supply up.
Yeah. Well, there you go. That's true.
Just tell people it doesn't work and
then uh just see the prices drop and
then uh buy it all for yourself. Um two
more two more comments. I did add this
one to Howard Davies, which did get uh
promoted near the top two, which I'm
very thankful for. So, thank you. Um
this next top stopping by to to commend
Nick uh on the insiders program. This is
kind of a self-promotion at this point,
but um it I promise it did get a bunch
of likes and got to the top, near the
top. Um commend Nick on the insiders
program and its separation from the main
channel. I don't feel like I'm missing
out on any on not subscribing to the
insiders. Uh that is to say, I don't
feel like I'm getting screwed into
signing up. I also think that the
adverts have been integrated really well
into all the videos. uh the script of if
you'd like more detail, you can find it
here with the other benefits isn't
intrusive and it gets the point across.
I hope it's uh worked well and
generating the revenue to support the
main channel. Thanks for the quality
content, Howard. Uh I really appreciate
it. I know you're probably not listening
to this uh but it's kind of an off
chance, but uh yeah, that was kind of
the goal. I I don't I don't want
uh
it's I'm not a huge fan of advertising,
but I have to advertise in every single
video. I mean, it sounds funny because I
have to advertise uh the insiders. It's
just the way it is. It's the it's
literally the only way that I make money
other than YouTube revenue. And I
promise you, YouTube revenue is not
paying in many of the bills. So yeah,
it's really just the the insiders or
bust. And I also don't want to get to a
point where it's like I'm not helping
people uh publicly in the public videos
and whatnot. So I have to I have to walk
this fine line of like how much
information I release. And I'm actually
going to cover more on the at the end of
this episode because I've got a few more
things to say that I won't get into
right now. But um yeah, in the end, I I
deeply appreciate it. I added this
definitely as a bit of self-promotion,
but also to to say thank you. Um it does
mean a lot to me when I get comments
about the insiders. It means especially
more to me simply because I put so much
work into improving the insiders and
that's why we do these live sessions and
uh I do a podcast every month for the
insiders as well. Um, and that's all
because I'm getting feedback from people
saying like, "Oh, can you can you do
this? Can you do that?" And I try to do
within the means of of what I have as a
oneperson operation. So, um, anyway,
I'll I'll get off go to the next topic,
but thank you, Howard. I deeply
appreciate it. Okay. Dave Chapel, not
Dave Chappelle, but Dave Chapel said,
"I've been taking creatine on and off
for decades. I've always known it
doesn't grow muscle. However, I've
always only gained muscle size when on
it. The reason is that whenever on
creatine, I work out harder and longer
because I had more energy. The study you
talked about has them doing this exact
same program.
So, as in they equate the volume between
the two. I don't know. But, uh, nobody
ever told me creatine grew muscle mass.
It was the effect on energy availability
to go harder, which is my layman
experience. Yeah. So you're exactly
right Dave that the primary mechanism
that's brought up is that it increases
the amount of phosphocreatine that's
found inside your cells which ultimately
leads to more uh recycling of ATP when
ATP is spent. So ATP being cellular
energy.
Okay. Uh last topic here let me get into
this. Uh non-nutritive sweeteners and
cognitive decline. So, this was one that
I recently covered and I wrote I think
the title was like I'm starting to worry
about artificial sweeteners. I use the
word artificial although it was about
non-nutritive sweeteners simply because
I think people recognize the word
artificial more than they recognize kind
of a tongue tying non-nutritive
sweeteners. So, but it did apply to a
number of different non-nutritive
sweeteners. And the ultimate conclusion
from this study, the result of this
study was that it was an associative
study and they were looking at a number
of I think like eight different
non-nutritive sweeteners and they showed
that there was an increase in cognitive
decline
uh more rapid cognitive decline if a
person consumes more non-nutritive
sweeteners as a whole uh compared to the
group that consumed very little. Now, in
addition to that, what I also mentioned
and they did do a bunch of uh because
this is associative and I think it was
over eight years or something like that.
It was several thousand participants,
but it was it was prospective. So, it
wasn't a retrospective study, which is a
weaker study design. This is a a
stronger study design, but it is still
associative. And they do a bunch of
adjustments for confounding variables.
And among those confounding variables,
they did address nutrition and they
addressed uh obesity, diabetes,
cardiovascular disease, and a bunch of
other uh potential reasons for why
cognitive decline might uh might be a
factor.
Now, that said,
why I came to this conclusion of I'm
starting to worry a little bit about
non-nutritive sweeteners is funny
enough, I think I think I didn't
emphasize this enough in my video, and I
think pe some people, the majority of
people got the idea, but some people
didn't get what I was saying. They
thought it was a little too extreme to
say that you might worry about
non-nutritive sweeteners.
And
the reason for that was not actually
based on this study alone. It was the
fact that when I looked at randomized
control trials, so I looked at uh a lot
of these different sweeteners and I
looked at randomized control trials
looking at cognitive different cognitive
uh outcomes. So looking at like yeah
verbal fluency or if that was like
recall or some sort of memory task or
there's a a a back test which is often
used in cognitive recall uh testing and
I was just stunned at how little
research exists.
So, I'm thinking to myself at this
point, I'm like, "Wait, wait, wait,
wait. So, we are deeming non-nutritive
sweeteners as safe and fine for
cognitive health, but we haven't
actually tested it. And now, on top of
that, we now have an associative study,
which easily, just like any other
associative study, could be flawed in
some way that we just don't know. uh
like they didn't adjust for a particular
something that uh we're just not
thinking of. Completely possible. I'm
not saying that we should base things
just on this one associative study. This
is it. We're done with non-nutritive
sweeteners. I still consume them. Um
my point being that there's such a lack
of evidence that I think it's perfectly
reasonable for a person to be like,
"Wait a second. I was under the
impression that we had all this research
actually proving that they were safe for
my brain. But now there's I'm realizing
there's almost for some of them there's
zero studies, no randomized control
trials indicating safety for the brain.
And now I'm supposed to just be like,
well, I'm just going to continue to
consume them as if I have all this
evidence to back it. No, that's I mean
so then it becomes more of a question of
what is your risk tolerance rather than
ah yes, I have all this evidence and I'm
just going to ignore it and say that
they're a negative for my health. Um
so and especially with so the big two
that I mentioned that that had the
greatest association was xylitol and
arythritol. of both of these sugar
alcohols. And it's funny because this
isn't the only analysis. There's
actually been multiple that I've covered
that that have also been associative,
largely associative, and they've also
identified arythritol and xylitol
separately as being related to other
negative health outcomes. So, at this
point now, I'm thinking like, man,
is it really fair to to just keep saying
that non-nutritive sweeteners are we
know the the key word there, know that
they are safe to consume for our brain.
I don't think we can jump to that
conclusion. I would challenge someone
and be like, well, okay, show me then.
Show me the evidence. Um it might be it
might turn out to be the case that we
will get randomized control trials that
do indicate a benefit. And to be clear
the other outcomes that have been tested
like for example improvements in like
insulin resistance or improvements in
body weight, body fat thing, body
composition as a whole. Yeah, no doubt.
Like we have many randomized control
trials and they all indicate benefits of
non-nutritive sweeteners. I do have a
few quibbles about sucralose because
that one has a lot of mixed literature,
but which I I think I covered like two
years ago, but for many of the others,
it's typically and even sucralose is
going to lead to to more weight loss and
fat loss, which is a net positive. I'm
not I'm not here to like ring the bell
and say, "Oh, we're we're definitely
this is doomsday, you know, stop all
non-nutritive sweeteners." I I will
again say I consume them. I still
consume them. But when I communicate
that to other people, I'm not going to
sit here and say like like for example
with the fat loss, I can I can point to
many randomized control trials and say,
"Look, we have the evidence indicating
it is perfectly safe and very effective
for weight loss and fat loss." And if
you want to use it for that, like you're
good to go. Um, however, if a person
says, "Hey, you know, I'm I'm having a
tough time thinking, like I feel kind of
brain fog and whatnot, and then they ask
me, "Hey, what what about non-nutritive
sweeteners? Can I still take them?" and
whatnot. Um, I mean, one, I'm not their
physician, but like, if they just wanted
my opinion, I would be like I I couldn't
sit there and point to a bunch of
evidence saying, "Yeah, they're just
perfectly fine." Um, I would I would
have to like sit down with them and have
a conversation and be like, "Look, we we
don't have very many studies on that
topic."
Uh, we have one associative study that
shows that there's a more rapid decline.
There are some issues with that
analysis, but, you know, they're not
huge as far as I can tell, and maybe an
epidemiologist might be able to correct
me. They did do sizable adjustments for
a lot of it.
the greatest risk for was for people
that are insulin resistant that have
diabetes. There was far less risk uh
almost no risk for people that don't
have diabetes that don't have insulin
resistance. Um and even in the the worst
case scenario, I still I it's not like
I'm sitting here thinking that
non-nutritive sweeteners are the cause
of cognitive decline. Absolutely not. I
think that they're a minor factor. But
you know my job is to look at the
research and analyze is there an effect
or is there not effect? If there is an
effect how much of an effect and I think
the answer is there could be an effect
and the effect is probably small
regardless even if there is an effect
it's probably pretty small. So that was
that was really the the idea for why I'm
worried. It's
because
I don't know about you, but I like to
have actual hard evidence indicating
yes, it's perfectly healthy. Like there
are plenty of mechanistic studies that
show cytotoxicity of cons of of applying
nut non-nutritive sweeteners, a wide
variety of them to cells leading to
death of those cells. And to be clear,
obviously this is mechanism research and
you're applying such astronomically high
concentrations
to the cells that unless you have proper
controls there, uh it's kind of hard to
say, oh yeah, this is biologically
relevant. probably not
especially at those doses because the
amount that's in the bloodstream is far
lower than what's found in uh in in
these cell studies. But now we're not
just basing it on the cell studies. Now
we have the first associative study
looking at cognitive decline. It is a
prospective study. They did a number of
different adjustments that I thought
were really really great. They looked at
the dose consumption at that's like
about the amount of one can of soda or
two cans of soda which was like the
highest level of consumption that they
measured. Um so
and then we we have a lack of randomized
control trials not for all the the
non-nutritive sweeteners but for for
many of them to look at something that I
think is perfectly reasonable to look at
like cognitive outcomes like we should
be able to to just like apply it acutely
you know just a single dose and then
measure what happens like does a
person's like memory uh get impacted
somehow and then have other studies that
last like 12 weeks of continuous
consumption at the dose that they were
using that they were looking at for the
associative study like maybe two cans of
soda or something and then measure and
see and if if those came back and said
hey there's nothing to worry about I
would ease off a little bit more I'd
still be a little uncomfortable because
the the the time scale of those studies
is only several months and the
associative studies looking over eight
years but I would still it would still
make me feel a lot better. Um, and even
now, even with this information that I
know now,
I'd still like to see more associative
studies. I'd like to see more like it's
I like to see some other labs approach
this from different directions and see
what they can come up with looking at
different data sets. So like if we were
to look at like NHANES data and and
quantify, okay, do we see more cognitive
decline? I don't think that they've
actually measured cognitive um like done
different cognitive tasks. So I think
that's probably not going to be
possible. But if we were able to to find
some other data sets that also looked at
cognitive outcomes
like memory, verbal fluency, and
whatnot, executive function, which is
these different brain uh brain outcomes,
I mean, I'd be fascinated to know what
other uh data is going to come out to to
to find this link. So initially I went
from I went my position went from
non-nutritive sweeteners are perfectly
safe. Uh I'm not worried about them and
I'll consume them at whatever quantity
that I want. I went from that to non-nut
non-nutritive sweeteners
have not as much evidence as I would
like but I still don't think and they
have a little bit of evidence against
them but I still don't think that
they're going to have a massive impact
on your cognitive health and I will
still consume it I still consume them
in small to moderate doses. Um, not that
I sit here and like just mass consume
them in general, but whenever I could
avoid it, like here I've got water and
sometimes I used to put non-nutrient
sweeteners in here. Now I'll put like
lemon juice or something like that, you
know, something pretty simple or I'll
just add nothing.
And it's really just like small shifts
like that. It's nothing crazy. You're
not going to see a video from me, at
least not based on this study, that's
going to have me with a shocked
expression and then it's going to be
like, "Avoid all non-nutritive
sweeteners from here on out." Uh, unless
yeah, we get some randomized control
trials that start saying, "Whoa,
we have just detected an effect that uh
we did not predict." Um, that would be a
big red flag. Right now it's kind of
like a went from a dark green solid
green flag to a slightly
lighter green flag trying to go to
yellow. It's not even at yellow yet. So
that's uh that's kind of where I stand
anyway. And you may your risk tolerance
may be much lower than mine and in that
case maybe you'll just cut them out if
it's no you know negative if it's not
going to impact your life in any
meaningful way. I mean, not not a big
deal. Okay, let's get into uh and I
guess I'll say for the other side and
other people may just need way more
evidence actually showing harm. Not just
a lack of evidence and this one
associative study, but actual randomized
control trials showing harm before
they'll even consider stopping
non-nutritive sweeteners, which I think
is a perfectly reasonable approach as
well.
Okay, number 69 said,
"I was part of a PhD's research into
artificial sweeteners in a rodent model,
cow, and highfat diet with uh reb.
I'll just say the um
one in parenthesis. Stevia is kind of
the scientific name. I'm not sure if
that's uh misspelled or not.
Ree rebioside.
Maybe that's correct. I've just haven't
seen it. So anyway, stevia and asulfane
K versus fructose and control. So
hisytologology of fat cells was
unaffected by artificial sweeteners with
normal and highfat diet. No impact on
offspring weight looking at influence in
gestation and no increase in
inflammation. So TNF alpha interlucan 6.
Uh the literature is very mixed. The
strongest potential effect might be on
intestinal bacteria and the signaling
pathways coming from that, but insulin
and glucose tolerance was unaffected in
our trials and nearly all papers.
Okay, so there you go. So there's uh and
that's true. I've, you know, again, I
looked at some of this uh this this
mechanistic research and it's true that
for some of the non-nutritive
sweeteners, there doesn't seem to be
much of a signal at all. So, and I can't
remember all of them off the top of my
head. I don't remember if I looked at
Stevia and ASEL fame K, but here uh
we're hearing that there is no effect.
Of course, I can't vet this comment. So,
just be be aware of that, but uh based
on the literature I've seen, it it has
also been mixed. Some of it shows no
effect, some of it shows negative
effects um when you're looking at the
mechanistic research. And of course,
this person is looking at fat cells,
which as we know from
the impact uh that artificial sweeteners
or non-nutritive sweeteners as a whole
have on fat loss that it tends to be
very much a net positive. So, would we
expect to see anything on fat cells? I
would say probably not, right? Uh but
would we? That's completely different
from what we're looking at for neurons
right in our brain or micro ga. So if
you were to look at TNF alpha and
interlucan 6 at in microg ga which are
the immune cells found in our brain um
would we see an effect? I don't know uh
to be honest and I can tell you from
some of the literature that there are
studies that show that there's an
increase in uh or some negative effects.
So again mixed research. Uh, Thiago
Zorta said, "To me this study seems low
quality, too. Just the fact that they
bundle up all the sweeteners into tiers
based on milligram consumption instead
of typical consumption
seems to be a major red flag. So instead
of consum doing zero consumption, one
can two cans or something like maybe
zero consumption, one to two cans and
then like
four to six cans or something like that
of diet soda and then looked at the
relationship.
I think that's fair. I I that was one of
my critiques that their their brackets
for the amount of milligram consumption
was kind of all over the place but on
top of that they had lumped all the
artificial sweeteners into one category.
So, as in like so like aspartame you'll
consume like I don't know 120 milligrams
but then for like I don't remember
exactly the the which one so don't quote
me on this but like acceul K is like
less than a milligram to get the level
of sweetness that you would normally
consume. So, if that's the case, then
you're and you're lumping it all
together and you're looking at uh 350 mg
of artificial sweetener. That doesn't
really tell you a whole lot about, you
know, what composition of that is made
up from asylame K versus aspartame. Now,
to be clear, they did break that apart.
That's in in for some of their analyses.
And they did uh identify arythritol and
xylitol as consistently even in
non-inssulin resistant individuals
having a relationship with uh more rapid
cognitive decline. Uh also I'm skeptical
of their cognitive decline being a line
instead of a curve that gets much
stronger towards uh the 80s.
Uh where is the control? So I think that
may be I mean that is a good point and
typically you would expect you know as
one ages that suddenly you would see a
pretty rapid decline. I'm not to be
honest I'm not sure if they showed it in
a I think what they were showing if I
had to explain it is they were showing
the rate of decline
although I guess that still wouldn't
explain it.
Either way, the data that they that they
base their conclusions off of was a rate
of decline per year. So, it was a
standardized measurement. It wasn't
looking at the absolute change over the
8 years or whatever it might be and
looking at different age categories. So,
they had like 50, 60, 70, 80, and they
had a line going down. It was perfectly
straight. And I think that may just be
the way that they were showing it. I'm
not entirely sure. There might there's
probably something there that I'm
missing.
So, I can't fully explain that to be
honest with you.
Uh, and where's the control? So, the
control is is the the low uh
non-nutritive sweetener consumption. Um,
that's very typical in a lot of
epidemiological studies. You're not
you're seldom going to find maybe not
for non-nutritive sweeteners. Maybe you
would find a group that a large enough
group that don't consume any whatsoever,
but the the low dose was very low. So it
was like way less than a single can of
soda. So they probably just from the
amount they can consume from I don't
know on once a week they maybe go to
7-Eleven or something and grab like
they'll have like a diet mound. I don't
know like whatever it might be. Uh
but in general they don't consume that
much. So they're as close to zero as you
can maybe get. uh in epidemiology that's
it's difficult to try to tease out those
groups because those groups tend to be
so far outside the normal again that may
not necessarily be the case for
non-nutritive sweetener specifically but
if you were to look at like
I don't know we we'll say uh people who
don't consume
people who consume less than 10 grams of
saturated fat okay saturated fat People
try to reduce that in general, but like
less than 10 grams or let's say even
more extreme, less than five grams, you
really have to work at not consuming
five grams of saturated fat. Like unless
maybe you're consuming a completely
plant-based, but even plant-based, there
are many saturated fats in like palm
oil, for example, coconut oil, you know.
So, and even olive oil has a little bit
of saturated fat in it. So, it's
primarily monounsaturated, but like it's
really hard to just like completely
avoid these different fats. So, you
know, finding enough people that would
fit a control of like zero saturated fat
or zero non-nutrient sweeteners or zero
meat consumption. That one's a little
little bit easier. But even then, you'd
have to look at a huge population just
to get enough people into that sample to
be able to compare everything against.
And if you don't, if you don't, the
consequence is that you have so much
uncertainty in the control that it
creates a lot of uncertainty in the
entire analysis because everything is
being compared against it. The medium,
the low non-nutritive sweeteners versus
the control, high non-nutritive
sweeteners versus the control, moderate
non-nutritive sweeteners against the
control. And if the control, the base of
your analysis is so uncertain, it
renders the whole analysis extremely
uncertain. So, there's arguments either
way, but um that part I didn't find uh
nearly as as bad. Uh also, I find it
very hard to believe that all these
sweeteners with completely different
chemical composition all cause the same
decline. Uh yes, that's true. So, that's
a great point and that's why like
looking at the data just all lumped
together can be
off-putting and it can be uh misleading.
So that's why they broke them up and
that's why I focused on specifically
mentioning the the main drivers were
arythrtol and xylitol
also too many factors being controlled
uh dilutes the confidence in the results
when the results are already mixed and
you already have uh another other
problems. Yeah. So like controlling for
different factors is always going to be
a tough ask and especially how you
control it. So, is it continuous or is
it categorical? Um, there's there's a
lot of considerations. So, that's why
again, I'm going to go back to my point
that we'd probably need more associative
studies and then we'd probably also I
would actually like to see the
randomized control trials before I
really start to wave a red flag over
here, you know. But, yeah, great points,
great push back. Um, some other comments
and questions people ask like was
Stevius uh assessed or sucralose
assessed? The answer is no. Um I have
done some separate stuff on sucralose
and insulin resistance and blood sugar.
I I think my conclusion was that the
evidence was quite mixed and I would
probably avoid sucralose if you are
worried about like insulin resistance. I
I don't think it's going to like send
you into diabetes or anything but you
know maybe has a really small effect at
kind of pushing you towards that. um
simply because the studies that I found
all randomized control trials were uh
you know some of them showed either
neutral effects maybe like a few of them
if I remember showed some positive
effects but there were several that
showed negative effects. So you know
again kind of that in that like how much
risk are you willing to take? Okay,
that's where I'm going to leave things.
Uh we've been talking for almost three
hours. I'm going to finish things off by
doing a little bit of housekeeping. I
keep this till the end um simply because
I don't want to bore people that don't
want to listen to this. But
I Yeah. So, when it comes to the videos,
I want to talk about the videos a little
bit because
over the over this past like six months
or so, I've been making subtle
adjustments actually since the beginning
of the year. At the at the end of the
year, I decided I'm going to start
adding a main points section at the end
of the videos. And that's because I was
getting this constant feedback of like,
well,
can you give me like the short version
of this? And I'm like, yeah, that's
fair. you you should be you should be
able to have everything kind of like put
together for you on the highlight points
of what's what's kind of the most
important takeaways and that's speaking
of takeaways that's the other thing I
wanted to work on make things that are
more applicable
even if we go over mechanism research to
be able to integrate that with the
clinical evidence and to say okay
sure this is fascinating mechanism
research but as always we can't base
things off of mechanisms. So, we have to
look for clinical research and is there
any clinical research?
So,
uh I've been I've been working on
integrating both of those ideas together
and I did that for about 6 months and it
was working out okay except I was
getting a lot of new feedback telling me
that the videos were too long and that
people didn't need to hear a lot of what
I was talking about. So, this one was
difficult because I was thinking to
myself, I'm just such a nerd. I love
talking about this stuff and I know
there are other people out there. Like,
I also get feedback from people saying,
"Hey, don't shorten the videos." So, now
I'm stuck between two groups of people.
But the thing is, if I don't shorten the
videos and if I don't cut away some of
the uh the the fat, the the juicy fat
that's like I enjoy, but um the juicy
fat around the the main parts of the
content,
the videos tend to not perform as well.
Some of them will perform really well
and then the majority will perform not
very well and the channel just doesn't
grow nearly as quickly as it probably
should. Um,
so I've been trying to strike this
balance of
making punchy videos that have high
applicability, high takeaway value with
everything summarized. Not everything,
but like the main points summarized at
the end while still giving a flavor, a
taste of that nerdiness of the of the
details. Like there's some times where
it's just like I don't I don't care what
anybody thinks. I I have to tell you
about
how butyrate interacts with your histone
diaetylates. just like real quick. Give
me like one minute to I I don't I'm not
going to bore you with the data
necessarily, but I am I just have to
quick mention it because it's just like
who wants to hear for the billionth time
fasting is good for your health or
eat protein to build muscle. Like who
gives a damn? I I we have heard that so
many times.
What's what people are here physionic
physio is phys based on physiology. It's
like understanding how your body works.
So being able to come to a video and not
just understand what the clinical data
says but also be able to understand like
why did why did that happen? Why did
people like for example with my FGF-21
video that I did? Why do people consume
less protein and then they see this this
significant metabolism boost as a
result? Like why does that happen? And
it comes down to this molecule FGF-21.
It's like I don't want to just say, "Oh
yeah, it's this molecule FGF-21." No,
it's like well how does it work? What's
it secreted from? How does it bind to
our receptors? Like where is it binding?
Why does it get released? like all these
things like there's so many questions
and so many things we can dive into and
I I don't want to lose that. Like that's
the heart of what makes physionic
special to me. I mean it's just what
makes me tick. I'd like to be able to
take a person on a journey, a
physiological journey, and have them
feel
and feel satisfied that, wow, okay, I
did not know that that, you know, I can
just tell you, oh yeah, a low protein
diet will increase your metabolism, but
like that's not that I guess that's
somewhat novel, but beyond that, you
probably want to know, well, why? And
how does that relate to the high protein
diets that also seem to increase
metabolism because the mechanisms by
which they work are completely
different? That's fascinating, right? So
I don't want to completely eliminate
that like and that's never going to
happen. I I I would just like I just
refuse to do that. So what I've done is
I've tried to truncate the videos to
make them punchier. Like I said, have
more takeaways, but also still fill in
some of that physiological gap, some of
that that the the mechanisms and whatnot
without necessarily beating you over the
head with the data. Um, and then when I
get into the really nitty-gritty, I just
save that for the insider content, which
I know makes some people grown that I
I'm leaving things for the insiders and
whatnot, but it's just I I'm
legitimately trying to make the
experience as good as possible, grow the
channel as as quickly as possible within
ethical means, and
also have enticing content for people
that just want to learn more And I
really love being able to have these
discussions with the insiders, which I
do in these live sessions that I do uh
with the podcast. I I do a podcast every
month for the insiders that goes over
the month's content, all the takeaways.
It lasts about an hour. It's much
shorter than this dril that that I did
today. But yeah, it's just like I need a
place to be able to like really nerd
out. and the other. Yeah. So, it's just
it's kind of a necessity for me to to
cut the video length and keep them as
informative and helpful as possible um
for for people while keeping the the I
think some of those intricacies and
whatnot for the uh for for the insiders.
So, for the insider versions of of the
video. So yeah, I I'm just I'm I'm just
detailing you how I'm thinking about
things. I'm still going to continue to
make adjustments. Certain
recommendations that people give me like
I I can see it in my data. Like I go
over my data analytics and whatnot on
the back end. And some of the stuff that
people have said for me to try, I'm like
I know that's not going to work because
I I can see it in the data. People don't
respond to some people's suggestions.
Um, I can't even think of any off the
top of my head. But yeah, anyway, the
point is that for you that just know
that I'm constantly adapting. I'm trying
to improve the content continuously.
Um, it's just uh it's just slow going
and I'm tinkering here and there. I
think this year was some pretty big
changes. The whole main point section at
the end uh I think went over pretty
well. um and making sure that things are
more takeaway driven instead of just
this is fascinating but like this is
fascinating plus this is how you apply
it. Um I think I think that's uh that's
been a big thing for me too. Okay. Uh I
think I think last podcast I mentioned
that I was going to be doing a
self-correcting podcast idea. So, the
idea behind this, and I've been thinking
about this this entire time, from last
podcast up until right now. The idea
behind this podcast
was that I was going to
have a guest interview that guest at
length about a topic or several topics
and then I was not going to publish that
uh interview until I went into the
literature, found studies to either
corroborate or refute
what that guest had said,
and then I was gonna have that guest
come back on and we were going to limit
the discussion to just what we had just
discussed. So filling in some of the
nuances, but I was also going to push
back against some of their takes based
on like literature that I had found. So
I'd probably send it to them and just
let them know, hey, I'm going to be
discussing this, this, and this like
this is, you know, just so they're not
like blindsided because they they would
need an opportunity to look over that
data and whatnot. So yeah, just just
have this more open format so it's kind
of a self-correcting. So then you would
know unless you don't trust me, which is
I mean if that's your thing then that's
fair. I don't know how you got to this
point of the podcast. You probably
shouldn't be listening to me anyway. Um
but assuming you trust me then I would
be
I I would make it a more a far more open
format so people would know that the
information that's being said is being
vetted. So, the first half of the
podcast, it would be more free flowing
and the second half would be a lot more
of this like digging deeper into the
details while having all the evidence at
hand. I love that idea. I really do. The
problem is I can't do it. Uh I have
thought about it a lot. As I mentioned,
it takes so much manpower. I mean, just
so much manpower. it would take me so
long to be able to release just a single
episode
and I just I don't have that kind of
time and I'm a This is it. This is
Physionic. You're looking at it. So, I
don't I'm going to be editing this
video. I do have some people that I work
with uh on a part-time basis that that
like edit, you know, the the physiotic
videos and whatnot, but beyond that,
like I'm the ideation. I'm the one who
creates like my rubrics. I do all the
research. Like I I I do all that stuff.
So, for me to sit there for for like a
two-hour episode or even a one-hour
episode and have a person talking at
length and I have to scrub through the
video and I have to uh like figure out
what they said and then I have to find
sources and then I have to bring them
back and then it would take me months
just for a single video. And honestly,
I mean, it would be it would be such a
drain on me from an energy perspective,
but also like monetarily, I think I
would lose out on so much because I and
plus I would I I think I would end up
resenting it just because I would feel
like I couldn't pursue some of that
those nerdy details. Like all I want to
do is read research,
distill it, and put it out there for the
world for people to understand what that
research says, which is the whole idea
behind physionic, learn your body. Um,
from the from the uh macro to the micro,
if you know that uh line from years ago
um and I just don't think that it's
possible if I had a team, which I don't
want a team. I don't want a bunch of
people. I don't want this to become like
some massive company. Um,
then I I would probably be able to do
it. I'd be like the diary of CEO or
whoever it might be, except fact
checked, you know. Um, and it would be a
unique thing. I think that it's a great
idea for someone to do, somebody with
with more capital, somebody with more
time, somebody with a team of people
that could sit there and and sift
through it and and and do the research
and then like, you know, get the get the
guests to come back on and have this
whole process uh work out. It's just
it's just not feasible for me. I I'm a
oneman operation largely, mostly. So,
yeah, it's just not feasible. Although I
I really love the idea. Um the other
thing is too like I I've been thinking
about just like the podcast in general
and I I've already pulled away largely
from having people on and I think I'm
going to completely nyx anyone being on
the podcast anymore. Not because I like
to hear myself talk,
but because I'm exactly afraid of that.
I'm just a I'm just kind of tired of
people coming on podcasts and just kind
of spewing their BS just everywhere and
people just lap it up and people we we
just don't have enough of like a
critical
like a fair critical mind of like okay
this person said that but is that
actually true? Like there's no evidence
with podcasts, right? Like okay I'll
give like Dr. Rhonda Patrick uh some
credit here. like she'll put up uh the
study title, like when a a guest says
something, she'll put up the study
titled um on the screen, which I think
is really cool. Um the same with with uh
Jill Carvalo. He he does a great job
because he'll put like reference number
six and then you can go into the
description and and click on uh
reference number six and whatnot, which
I I really like, but it's just it's so
much work. And again, for the vast
majority of the time, it's just uh yeah,
it's just impossible. So, I just don't
think I'm going to have people on for
the podcast specifically. What I am
probably still going to do is have
people on the channel and what I'm going
to do is highly edit. So, I'll have a
small conversation with them in private,
like a 30 minute recorded conversation
on a very particular topic that they
know a lot about. And then I will do I
will do kind of like a mini version of
what I'm talking about. This like
self-correcting thing where I will then
go and check after the references and
I'll do a fully edited episode like a
video that I like I usually do and
feature that person. But at least then
you know that I've factchecked
everything they've said um because I've
taken the time and it's it's a much
smaller format. So, I only have to fact
check maybe five to 10 minutes of them
talking as opposed to a whole hour or
two hours or whatever it might be. So, I
think that's the direction I'm going to
go. And the podcast will just be me
ranting on this couch. Uh that it's
probably going to be a negative for a
lot of people, but that's just it's just
the way it is. At least I know, you
know, with my notes and my hopefully not
demented brain that uh I will be able to
just give more context and engage with
the comments of what people post under
some of the the most what I find the
most interesting uh posts, which is what
I I did uh today in this episode.
Let's see. Um, I did mention
the insiders, physionic insiders. I'm
going to mention it one more time. Um,
it's the only way that I support myself.
Uh, well, I do some consulting, but like
largely this is the the primary way that
I uh support myself. If you like this
kind of podcast, this was way more free
flowing than what I do for the insiders.
For the insiders, it's it's about an
hour long. Um, sometimes 45 minutes,
sometimes like an hour and 15 minutes.
and it's much punchier. So, I go through
each every single investigation that
come releases for the insiders. Um, and
then I have a takeaway section at the
very end. So, I'm like, uh, you know, if
this, then this, you know, then that.
So, I I Yeah, like I said, it's much
punchier.
And the whole goal is just to go over
all that month's content in one episode.
So, if you're interested, check out the
Physionic Insiders. It's linked in the
description. Um, no pressure, obviously.
Uh, it releases once a month. You also
get a private podcast link, so you can
access it, uh, through Spotify or Apple
Podcast or whatever, Stitcher, whatever
you like to use. Um, and you'll just get
updated every month. Um, it's not the
first of every month. It's like the
first like seven days or so of the the
month, but I have released an episode
every month for the last like year and a
half. Um, I'm very consistent with it. I
never miss a month. And you also get a
ton of other perks like I've mentioned
in all my videos. Um, if you want to
engage with live sessions with me, I do
those. Uh, you also get articles. You
can have those sent to your email. Um,
and a bunch of other stuff. I'm not
going to bore you with with all the
details, but yeah. And the the last
thing I want to say, which I always want
to finish with this, um, look, I I
always deeply appreciate anybody who's
along for the physionic journey. It's as
simple as that. I I I'm a highly
ambitious person, but I am also highly
focused on the ethics of like the
business side of physionic. and I'm
constantly taking feedback and trying to
improve wherever I can. There are
limitations. Um, some things would just
like bankrupt me if I if I did them. Um,
so and I also,
like I said, I just don't want physionic
to be this like
that. Have you ever Okay, let me put it
to you this way. Have you ever followed
like a YouTuber or just like social
media person? And I hate calling myself
a YouTuber, but I technically am on
YouTube.
just like a social media person who's
like they they started out small and
then they grew and grew and grew and
then they started growing into like oh
what welcome Chad to the team and like
Barry to the team and Natalie and like
and then they grow and there's nothing
wrong with growing but then they grow to
a point where it's like everything
becomes
so polished and so it
I think it's almost unintentional They
get into this position where they have
no flexibility because they've taken on
so many sponsorships or they've taken on
so many uh connections with people or
they've grown this thing that now they
have to they've employed all these
people so they can't be as free as they
were before.
And I really think that's just because
now they have so many people that depend
on them for money that and which is a
great thing. It's a beautiful thing to
be able to build a business to the point
where people are, you know, depend on
you and you have all these employees and
you can foster a great environment for
for these people and a job, right? So
that they can feed their families and
all that good stuff. But there are
downsides to that, right? And I I know
of many over the many years I've been
like just been watching t YouTube, I
know of many examples of people that
have like grown and grown and grown and
then they just kind of like lose sight
of
I don't want to say necessarily the
ethics although sometimes it is the
ethics but just this like
sense of appreciation just keeping
things simple that I think that's my
point just keeping things simple.
And as much as I'd like to tear my like
undergo mitosis and like have different
versions of myself just like all working
on all these different projects that I
have that I would love to do. Um I think
that the best course of action is just
to keep things um small. I mean
obviously still grow as much as I can
but like not have this pressure of
having all these people depend on me. Um
because I think on the front end it
allows me to
be
authentic. I kind of hate that word, but
we'll use it anyway. To be authentic and
to just have these conversations and
uh not really care that much uh because
I have wonderful people like you that
support me and I don't and it's just me,
right? So I don't have to like I don't
have to worry about like hey I need to
be selling selling selling because I
have to be paying all these other people
behind me that are helping me throughout
this thing all these employees because
that's just not the case. So yeah I mean
just I realize I'm kind of like ranting
and kind of thinking off the top of my
head but I just again I just wanted to
say thanks. It it means the world to me
to physionic is my job. Like that is
crazy to me. And I'm going to continue
to push it as far as I can. And it's not
like it's going to stop. It's not like
I'm going to suddenly be like, well,
I've read all the studies done. I've got
nothing else to say. That is not going
to happen. There's too much. There's
there's many lifetimes of content that I
could produce and it and studies I could
analyze and things I could learn. And I
have another 30, 40, hopefully 50 years
ahead of me.
Uh, man, knock on wood.
Uh, that I can continue to do this. And,
uh, yeah, it's it's all possible simply
because people like you actually, uh,
listen or watch or engage or make funny
comments like, "Zappy." Uh, yeah, I do
know some of your your YouTube comment
names and I do recognize them. Um,
Little Voice is another one that that
pops up. Cookie, definitely Cookie
Cupcakes. Um, yeah, just like there
there's just like so many people that I
could rattle off the names and just say
thank you to, but in general, just like
if you're listening to this, thank you.
I really do appreciate it. Um,
yeah. I can't promise when the next
episode will be. Uh, but
you know, it'll release at some point.
Fizzyang's not going anywhere. So, until
then, thanks for listening to me ramble
about stuff.
And, uh, yeah, have a great day. See
you.